<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The fair extravagant, or, the humorous bride. An English novel</title>
            <author>Oldys, Alexander.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 199 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 96 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90136</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O264B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R229887</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895718</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895718</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153254</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90136)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153254)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2357:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The fair extravagant, or, the humorous bride. An English novel</title>
                  <author>Oldys, Alexander.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 48, 25-48, 73-178 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Charles Blount, at the Catherine-Wheel at Charing-Cross,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed A. O.</note>
                  <note>A. O. = Alexander Oldys.--Wing (CD-ROM edition).</note>
                  <note>Text and register continuous despite pagination.</note>
                  <note>Wing reports imprint as: "For C. Blount".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:153254:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153254:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153254:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153254:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153254:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153254:3"/>
            <head>To my Worthy Friends, Mr. <hi>W.C.</hi> and Mr. <hi>A.P.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>AD it not been a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment, I had not preſum'd (Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen) to have occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned you a Bluſh, in throwing ſuch a Trifle as this unto your Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.
<pb facs="tcp:153254:4"/>
And yet, I fear, that what I deſign as an Expreſſion of my Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude for your many Favours, may draw on me a greater Obligation from you; I mean in receiving this into your Patronage: It is the firſt thing I have done publick Pennance for in a Sheet: Which, yet, had Mr. <hi>Blount</hi> been leſs haſty, had been more Correct and Pardonable.
<pb facs="tcp:153254:4"/>
You know the Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that provoked me to this Attempt; I ſhall only put you in mind, that—
<q>
                  <l>Nil habet Infaelix Paupertas durius in ſe,</l>
                  <l>Quam quod Ridicules ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines facit!</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall not need to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you with the <hi>Engliſh</hi> on't, to whom the <hi>Latin</hi> is as familiar and eaſy as your own <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue: Nor wou'd I
<pb facs="tcp:153254:5"/>
have the Ladys under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it, leſt it ſpoil my Fortunes.</p>
            <p>I muſt confeſs there is much in that! But there will be infinitely more in your goodneſs, if you will not, for this, leſſen the kind opinion you have hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto had of, moſt Dear Friends!</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt ſenſibly Oblig'd, Obedient and Humble Servant, <hi>A. O.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:153254:5"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Fair EXTRAVAGANT</hi> OR, THE Humorous Bride. AN <hi>ENGLISH</hi> NOVEL.</head>
            <p>IT is expected (perhaps) I ſhould ſay ſomthing by way of Introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to this Diſcourſe, an play the Philoſopher before I play the Poet. But at preſent I am not diſpoſed to be ſerious; beſides I never was fond of that tedious Paradox, the fartheſt way about, is the neareſt way home,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:153254:6"/>
and ſo am willing to be Trudging on to the Story, which tells us:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ariadne</hi> was as Beautiful as any of her Age, as Witty as Fair, as well Educated, and as Humorous as either; Add to theſe the advantage of her Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle's Death, who left her ſole Heireſs to Twelve Hundred Pounds a Year, beſides ſome Thouſands in Money and Jewels, and you will conclude he was the happieſt younger Brother in <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom</hi> that Married her: And ſo (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps) he was; for I never heard her Virtue call'd in queſtion; and 'tis hard if a Man could miſcarry among ſo many Excellencies; at leaſt it muſt be his own fault. Her Birth two was Honourable enough, being Daughter to a Knight Baronet, by which you may gueſs ſhe was an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Woman and our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; for (by the way) I am not going to put any <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Intrigue upon you.</p>
            <p>The laſt fatal time ſhe was in Town, being about the ſeventeenth year of her Reign, (for Beauty, give me leave to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:153254:6"/>
tell you, has a large Empire) ſhe Lodged, — let me ſee! ſomewhere a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout St. <hi>James's.</hi> I need not deſcribe her Lodgings to you, I muſt only ſay, they were agreeable to her Humour and Fortune, which made 'em both ſplendid and pleaſant, being richly hung and adorn'd with Cabinets, Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, Glaſſes and what not! But much more with excellent Pictures of the beſt Hands, and thoſe cheifly in her Cloſet, where (if ever you were there) you might have obſerved that of <hi>Don Quixot,</hi> and <hi>Sancho Panca,</hi> which hung juſt over againſt <hi>Amadis de Gaul,</hi> and directly oppoſite to <hi>Oroondates</hi> and <hi>Caeſario</hi> in Combat when they had miſtaken one another; with many more fantaſticks. Nor were her Books better match'd. Here you might ſee <hi>Frances Quarles</hi> bound up with <hi>George Withers,</hi> Sir <hi>John Suckling</hi> and Sir <hi>John Denham, Randolph</hi> and <hi>Broom, Shakeſpear</hi> and <hi>Johnſon</hi> (though they could hardly ever agree before) <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>Fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cher</hi> (you know) always wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> together; many other Modern
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:153254:7"/>
Poets were pil'd in a heap; my Lord <hi>Rocheſter</hi> was laid aſide, only Mr. <hi>Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi> ſtood alone: but what was moſt pleaſant of all, this ſatyrical pretty Lady had bound <hi>Rablais</hi> with <hi>Dod</hi> upon <hi>Clever.</hi> In ſhort, here lay a Play, there a Sermon; here an Academy, there a Prayer-Book; here a Romance, and there a Bible: not but that ſhe was a good Chriſtian for all this I dare ſay. Now be pleaſed to take notice, when ſhe was weary of ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and dancing, ſhe did often read in one or other of theſe Books, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Romances, for ſhe was a great lover of Knight Errantry, and was a little <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> way addicted, as I fear you'l find, ſhe had had the tender of many Hearts, the proffers of many a fair Service, but either this was a Squire, or that a Clown, or t'other a Fop, and ſo to the end of the Chapter: ſhe never yet had liked any ſo well as to M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>y, One day, being very long and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> at her Devotion, I mean, her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> on a ſuddain ſhe ſtarts up and run<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a Couſin of hers, whom ſhe l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:153254:7"/>
dearly. My heart (ſaid ſhe) I am reſolved on't, my own <hi>Miranda</hi> (ſhe continued) it muſt be. I am confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the reaſonableneſs of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and I will go through with it; therefore make haſt and prepare to ſecond me. — The young Lady her Couſin was ſurpriſed, but knowing her humour pretty well, ſhe ſtraight con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded there was ſome frolick intended, and boldly ſaid, Lead on (my Dear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>) Ile follow thee, aſſured that ſtill thy Virtue will guide us always. Perhaps (reply'd <hi>Ariadne</hi>) the zealous and the ſcrupulous may at this time call it in queſtion, but thou ſhalt be my Judge. Know then (thou tender'ſt part of my Soul!) I am juſt now weary of that o'repreſſing weight of a Maidenhead, which I have labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red under theſe five long years; and ſince I have not been Courted by any man to whom I could engage my ſelf for ever and for Ay, I am reſolved we will put on two of my Brothers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and ramble all the Town over, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> will meet with the man with
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:153254:8"/>
whom I can find in my heart to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the dangerous Sin of Matrimony. Thou wilt be witneſs of all my acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which I hope ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>er coſt thee a Bluſh, Ah (deareſt friend) reply'd <hi>Miranda,</hi> I know your Virtue keeps too ſtrict a Guard, to permit any thing to be acted contrary to it's Prerogative, 'tis abſolute and allowes but few priviledges to the Subject, but thoſe moſt wholeſome and pleaſant; and for this little extravagance you have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, I think it ſo Innocent, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally reguarding the deſign that leads you, that I proteſt I am fond of it my ſelf. Come along then (ſaid <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adne</hi>) let's to my Brothers Chamber and dreſs! 'tis now about three a Clock, and <hi>Evander</hi> (that was her Brothers name) is juſt gone out to take a Bottle before Play-time: How know you t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t? (ſaid her Couſin,) As I ſate in my Cloſet (reply'd <hi>Ariadne</hi>) I heard him ask if the Coach were ready? 'twas anſwer'd yes, upon which he went down ſtairs. This bleſſed op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity muſt not eſcape us, by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:153254:8"/>
means (ſaid her loving Second.) With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out making any more words there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they went directly to <hi>Evanders</hi> Wardrobe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> fitted themſelves with two of the richeſt, and moſt modiſh Suits that were there, which indeed were very Glorious and faſhionable: for by the way, <hi>Evander</hi> was a Spark of the firſt Rate, his Father having left above 3000 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> a year, clear Eſtate in Land, beſides a conſiderable bank of Money. He was very good hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour'd and very handſom, much like his Siſter, and very little Taller; four years older than ſhe, being juſt turn'd of twenty one. However were he twenty Brothers, and twenty times more like her, than he was, ſhe was mighty glad of his Abſence, for they immediately dreſt themſelves, and the Cloaths ſate very well on 'em, being all three much of the ſame height and proportion. Now (ſaid <hi>Miranda</hi>) Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin, Marry aſſoon as you will, I would adviſe you not to part with the Bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, for I vow to you they become you extreamly well! Pardon me <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randa</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:153254:9"/>
(ſaid our t'other <hi>Amazon</hi>) if I take not your advice, for I ſhould per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly hate my Husband, if I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd he would ſuffer me to impoſe on him. But come Child (continued ſhe) let's ſee if the Coaſt be Clear, and whip out the back way: ſaying ſo, down the Back-ſtairs they went into the Garden, which Door they preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unlock'd, <hi>Ariadne</hi> conſtantly keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Key of it about her, afterwards they rambl'd as far as <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> and the crowd going in, and coming out, at <hi>Richard's</hi> Coffee-houſe, ſtopt 'em, which made <hi>Ariadne</hi> curious to know the humours of ſuch a Place, with much ado then they thruſt in boldly and ſate 'em down: ſays one, who ſate at the Table where they were, In my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion the <hi>Character</hi> of a <hi>Popiſh</hi> Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is as Rational a Diſcourſe as has been writ of late, nor can I think that Mr. <hi>L' Strange</hi> has any way anſwer'd his leaſt Objections to the <hi>D's</hi> Succeſſion. O (cry'd <hi>Ariadne</hi>) a delicate peice 'tis, no doubt! And if he had but apply'd himſelf never ſo
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:153254:9"/>
little to the Lord Mayor, and Court of Aldermen, immediately upon the Death of Mr. <hi>Jordan;</hi> in reward he had certainly obtain'd the Honour of being Poet to the Honourable City of <hi>London,</hi> before any the moſt preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Competitor in Town. 'Twas a ſtrange overſight in him (reply'd <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>da</hi>) but I underſtand now he ſets up for ſomthing more Advantageous; I mean, to be Cheif-Firework Maker to the forementioned Honourable City, upon their uſual Solemnities on the 5th. and 18th. of <hi>November:</hi> and it is ſaid he deſigns to Burn his own <hi>Pope Joan</hi> next Year. Why, <hi>Sir!</hi> (ſaid another that ſate by) do you imagin it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves ſo ill a fate? And that Mr. <hi>S.</hi> Writes ſo mean a Stile, that it may only become a Pageant. No pardon me, <hi>Sir,</hi> (reply'd <hi>Ariadne</hi> taking up the Cudgels for her friend) we here no ill opinion of your Author, for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly I like his Scenes of Love and Gallantry very well: but my friend <hi>Elkanah</hi> had been more highly to be commended, had he left off before he
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:153254:10"/>
came to <hi>Pope Joan</hi> and the <hi>Character &amp;c.</hi> I ſuppoſe (ſaid another neat ſpruce Spark in a Band) you are a <hi>Tory.</hi> A <hi>Tory! Sir,</hi> (cry'd <hi>Ariadne</hi>) whats that? That is, a <hi>Tantivy-man,</hi> a <hi>Dukes-man,</hi> or a <hi>Papiſt</hi> in <hi>Maſquerade.</hi> On my word (ſaid <hi>Miranda</hi>) 'tis of a large ſignification! But I can aſſure you <hi>Sir,</hi> we are none of all theſe. Perhaps (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinu'd ſhe) we wiſh the <hi>D.</hi> all the Right imaginable: ſo do I too, (repli'd our Spark with the Band) but then I fear it will go very hard with him. Pray <hi>Sir,</hi> (continued he very pertly) don't you think the late Parliament diſſolv'd at <hi>Oxford,</hi> were all wiſe and honeſt, well meaning Gentlemen? How <hi>Sir!</hi> (cry'd <hi>Ariadne</hi> very briskly) All w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap> and honeſt! that can't be, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> muſt be ſome Fools, and ſome Knaves, or elſe they are not the true Repreſentatives of the People. At this, ſome laugh'd, and ſome look'd Unplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly. On my word young Gentlemen (ſaid Sir <hi>Formal</hi> with his Band) 'tis well our Preſident is not here, for he wou'd have had about with you before
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:153254:10"/>
now. About with us? (reply'd <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adne</hi>) what before all this Reverend Company? No, no, let him take about with his Boys, for we are not for his Management. However, (continu'd ſhe) 'tis time for us to be gone, for fear he ſhou'd ha' ſeen us at <hi>Paris</hi> or <hi>Validolid,</hi> or ſomewhere abroad where neither of us have been theſe forty Years. With theſe words they mov'd their Hats as they had ſeen others do, and left the Company to cenſure 'em; they tript on to the <hi>Dukes</hi>-Play-houſe, where that day was plaid the <hi>Orphan,</hi> or the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nhappy-Marriage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the way (ſaid <hi>Ariadne</hi>) I am ſure none of thoſe Fellows we left are for my turn. They got into the Pit, before they were aware, and <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adne</hi> had forgotten the Name of the Play. Prithee <hi>Jack</hi> (ſays ſhe to <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randa</hi>) what's play'd to day? The— ſomething, or the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nhappy-Marriage,</hi> (anſwer'd ſhe.) How! (ſaid t'other in a ſurpriſe) pray Heaven it prove not Ominous! Which is enough to convince any charitable Man that ſhe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:153254:11"/>
vvas a good <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> for I dare aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re him, her Prayers were heard. — Well — But — As ſhe vvas thus piouſly reflecting, a Gentleman vvho ſate near 'em, and vvhom ſhe had not as yet obſerv'd, over heard her Depreca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and taking notice of the Zeal vvith vvhich ſhe utter'd 'em. <hi>Sir,</hi> (ſaid he) you miſtake, poſſibly; this is not St. <hi>Pauls Covent-Garden,</hi> nor St. <hi>Dunſtan's</hi> Church; and indeed I beleive it is not ſo proper a place to Pray in. Hovv (ſaid ſhe ſmartly) I'm ſure I have heard many a good Sermon here, and I knovv no reaſon but that I may add a Prayer to 'em if I pleaſe; for aſſure your ſelf I have found it very vvhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſo to do. Nay, and more than that, I have on the contrary humm'd a Minuet to my ſelf, vvhen I have ſeen many a Reverend Spark in a Caſſook hold forth ſtoutly, and have nevertheleſs found no hurt by it at all I am ſorry <hi>Sir</hi> (ſaid he) you have perverted both the Places. Perverted (cry'd <hi>Ariadne,</hi> looking earneſtly on him) I think I made the prop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:153254:11"/>
uſe of them according to the times and Circumſtances, for there I have heard ſuch Hum drum Diſcourſe, that I muſt of neceſſity have fallen aſleep, had I not ſung in my own defence. Now here I have often taken notice of ſome Scenes that have ſo patly fitted the Circumſtances, which I was then un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that I could not forbear ſaying <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> to them. (Said <hi>Polydor,</hi> for ſo the Gentleman was call'd,) I ſee <hi>(Sir)</hi> you value your ſelf much on your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the Clergy and things Sacred, but I can aſſure you, no man in his right Senſes will eſteem you e're the more for it. And pray <hi>(Sir)</hi> give me leave to ask you how long tis ſince you read Mr. <hi>Hobbs's Leviath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>?</hi> for, I ſuppoſe you are mighty converſant with his No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Hum! — (ſaid ſhe ſcornfully) you will pardon me <hi>(Sir)</hi> if I do not well know whether you mean a Book or a Monſter by the Name. The laſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly (cry'd <hi>Miranda.</hi>) You are very poſitive, <hi>Sir</hi> (ſaid <hi>Polydor,</hi>) and have ſoon determined on my thoughts. But by good fortune you are in the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:153254:12"/>
right; for, if things that have no reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance to the other part of the whole Creation, may juſtly be call'd Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous; this is ſo. Ha! (ſaid <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adne,</hi> whiſpering <hi>Miranda</hi>) This is the Man. I confeſs (continued ſhe tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to <hi>Polydor</hi>) to prevent any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſcourſe on this matter, I have heard before of this old Gentleman, but I never gave my ſelf the trouble to be better acquainted with him, than by Hear-ſay. You are the happier man, <hi>Sir</hi> (ſaid <hi>Poloydor</hi>) for certainly you have avoided giving your ſelf a great deal of Perplexity. — By this time the Curtain was drawn up, and they ſuffered them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be entertained by the Players. And truly they did themſelves no great Violence, for I think 'twas a good Play. They had however ſome Diſcourſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Acts, which (perhaps) was more Harmonious than the Muſick, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially to <hi>Ariadne,</hi> who was ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly pleaſed with our younger Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, (for ſo was <hi>Polydor</hi>) that ſhe had engaged to go with him to <hi>Lockets</hi> after the Play. Now ought I in courſe, to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:153254:12"/>
give you a Character of this ſame <hi>Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor,</hi> and ſo I will. — He had lived about thirty Years, and thoſe cheifly in <hi>Paris</hi> and <hi>London,</hi> and a good <hi>Chriſtian</hi> too was he. I mean no <hi>Papiſt,</hi> nor yet a <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> but (perhaps) of Mr. <hi>Leſtrange's</hi> Faction, if I may call the Church of England a factious Party; but pardon me, I think it more proper to name thoſe ſo, who diſſent from it. For pray take notice I mean to repreſent him as he was, a very honeſt brave Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, of a good Family, well educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and of good natural Parts; for his Singing and Dancing I cannot ſay much, but of his Poetry, the Town has had ſufficient opportunities to Judge. He was as handſome too as the beſt <hi>Here</hi> I have ever ſeen upon our Stage. Not ſo cruel as <hi>Almanzor,</hi> nor yet ſo timerous as Sir <hi>Nicholas Culley.</hi> Not ſo vain as Sir <hi>Fopling,</hi> nor ſo plain as my wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipful friend Juſtice <hi>Cloapate.</hi> In ſhort, he was a very deſerving man, you may believe, for I have drunk ſome Bottels with him. He had an excellent virtue too beſides all theſe, which you will have
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:153254:13"/>
occaſion to obſerve: I mean his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy. This was therefore the Man on whom our fair <hi>Amazon</hi> had already thrown her ſelf away. To <hi>Lockets</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they went in a Coach together, where my dear friend <hi>Polydor</hi> loſt twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Guinneys, which both the Maſque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rading Ladies were witneſſes of, but they obſerved him ſo undiſturbed at it, that they concluded him a <hi>Stoick.</hi> Said <hi>Ariadne</hi> to him, Tempt your Fortune (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>) once more, here are ſome Guin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys at your ſervice. Pulling out a Purſe that held forty or fifty, truly I cannot tell which. I thank you, <hi>Sir,</hi> (ſaid <hi>Polydor,</hi> very obligingly,) but I muſt not accept them. I have loſt alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy what I propoſed to my ſelf to hazard, beſides I am yet ſo much a Stranger to you that I ought not in modeſty to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſo great an obligation of you, for I have not as yet forgotten that the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher ſaid. <hi>Qui beneficium accepit, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ent a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om vendidit.</hi> Pray what is that <hi>(Sir)</hi> in Engliſh? (ſaid <hi>Miranda.</hi>) O <hi>Sir!</hi> (replied <hi>Polydor</hi>) I am ſenſible of my want of breeding, and I know it was
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:153254:13"/>
an Errour to ſpeak Latin in Gentlemens Company, eſpecially in ſuch a Place. No matter (ſaid <hi>Ariadne</hi>) ſince we know <hi>(Sir)</hi> you will not accept of my Service. But (proceeded ſhe) I have a propoſition to make to you, if you can find in your heart to divorce your ſelf from this good Company, and drink a Bottle or two with my Coſin and me in another Room. I could wiſh you would Sir (ſaid <hi>Miranda</hi>) for I vow to you I am uneaſy among ſo many Strangers. Call then for another Room (ſaid <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lydor</hi>) and I will wait on you immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Gentlemen. I will but juſt take my leave here. They did ſo, after having made their Conge to our Gameſters, and expected him not long: but no ſooner were they gone, e're one enquired who they were? Another, whether they would Play? A third, what Eſtate either of them had? And how long he had known them? Nay god (ſaid he) I have not been long acquainted with them; tho one of them is a Relation of mine: which was that? (cry'd his friend <hi>Harry.</hi>) Why, he that offered me
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:153254:14"/>
Money, (anſwered <hi>Polydor.</hi>) Dam thee for a Coxcomb, (ſaid his other friend <hi>Tom</hi>) for refuſing it! No no (interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted our third Gamſter) I fancy he has better Buſineſs with him hereafter. You may ſwear it <hi>Will</hi> (ſaid <hi>Polydor</hi>) the Gold and I had not parted elſe, at leaſt this Night; for be pleaſed to take notice, I ſhould not have played an Ace more. Well — However ſit down and drink a little more for the Money thou haſt loſt already (ſaid honeſt <hi>Will.</hi>) No faith (cry'd <hi>Polydor</hi> going out) I am enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged. He went directly to his new Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, who (perhaps) were very glad to ſee him ſo punctual: and after having ſaluted him a freſh, (ſaid <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adne</hi>) Let us now lay aſide all formali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, for if you pleaſe (Sir) I mean to be very intimately acquainted with you. (A pretty ſort of a Phraſe, had he known who ſpoke it.) It will undoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly be my unhappineſs if I be not, (ſaid <hi>Polydor.</hi>) You do not know (cry'd ſhe very pleaſantly) how it would contribute to the whole felicity of my Life, if you vvould but endeavour
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:153254:14"/>
it. Hovv do you mean Sir? (anſvve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Polydor</hi> by the vvay of Queſtion.) I mean (ſaid ſhe) that all things might be in common betvveen us tvvo. For believe me, I vovv it moſt ſacredly to you: vvere I a Woman, you are the only man I muſt love. Hovvever I vvill novv make you an offer that may not (happily) be vvholly diſadvantage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to you, though it vvill add much to my Quiet. — Dear Sir (Interrupted <hi>Polydor</hi>) pray ſpare your Complements, and aſſoon as you pleaſe propoſe if you can what I dare refuſe to you. Come! To the Buſineſs; to the Buſineſs, Couſin, (ſaid <hi>Miranda.</hi>) You ſhall know then Sir (continued <hi>Ariadne</hi>) I have a Couſin that is a rich Heireſs, being at preſent poſſeſſed of twelve hundred pounds a year in Land, beſides ſome thouſand pounds in Money and Jewels: her Perſon is Tolerable, I think at leaſt it is ſo, if mine may be thought ſo; for we are more like than any other two you ever ſaw. Her humour I think exceeds that Pardon me (interrupted <hi>Miran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi>) they are both ſo excellent, that it
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:153254:15"/>
is no eaſie matter to determine which is moſt Beautiful and Charming. She is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to you (ſaid <hi>Ariadne</hi>) her Age (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſhe addreſſing her ſelf to <hi>Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor</hi>) is the ſame with mine, being very near Seventeen. You may believe in theſe Circumſtances ſhe could never want the Addreſſes of many Perſons, and thoſe (perhaps) of no mean Quality. But ſhe is very curious in the choice of that fatal thing we call a Husband, for (I dare ſwear for her) ſhe means to make no Property of him, but to love him as immoderately, unmodiſhly, and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> virtuouſly as ever Husband was loved, in the old Sacramental days of Matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny! And were ſhe mine, (interrupted <hi>Polydor</hi> I would love her ſo heartily ſhe ſhould almoſt complain on it: Not that I mean to kill her with kindneſs, for if I ſhould attempt that, I die firſt my ſelf, but I beg your pardon. Pray, Sir, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed: I muſt then remind you (purſued ſhe) how difficult it has been hitherto for any man to make the leaſt impreſſion on her Inclinations, which ſhe is ſo ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of, that ſhe almoſt deſpairs of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:153254:15"/>
finding a man ſhe could heartily love. I have often heard her though deſcribe ſuch a Figure of a Lover and of ſuch Qualifications to her ſelf, which made me once offer my Service to her in the ſearch of ſuch a one ſhe had deſcribed, inſinuating that I was the more likely to Succeed of the two, and the ſooner; becauſe my Breeches would admit me into that Company, which her Petticoats would exclude her. She readily accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted my offer, and was pleaſed to ſay, ſhe was certain ſhe ſhould approve of my Choice. And now this very minute am I playing the Knight Errant to ſerve this Lady, which I would do with the hazard of my life, for aſſure your ſelf I love her as my own heart. You were ſaying (Sir interrupted <hi>Polydor</hi>) ſhe gave you a Figure of the man ſhe could love, pray what was that Sir? If it be not rude in me to deſire it, nor inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient in you to ſhew it. I beg you would proceed to his Picture. You ſhall have it Sir, (ſaid ſhe) aſſoon as I can get yours drawn. As for your humour you are ſufficiently acquainted
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:153254:16"/>
with that already; for your Quality, I know it by your Name. So that to ſave the expence of ſo much pretious time, I am ſure you need only conſult your Glaſs, and you will ſee the very Man therein all Circumſtances. O Dear Sir! (ſaid <hi>Polydor</hi>) do not Impoſe on me, but I perceive this is but real Raillery, you have a mind to be merry: But, Come, Sir, my Service to you; this Glaſs will inſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire us with another and (perhaps) as pleaſant diſcourſe. She ſaw him drink off his Glaſs fairly: And then anſwered, By all the truth Mankind is capable of, you do me wrong (Sir) to imagin that I have hitherto impos'd on you, or that I ſhall ever hereafter endeavour it; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, I am very ſenſible 'tis no eaſie at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt in any body, eſpecially in me. Yet, give me leave once more to attack your unjuſt, and if I may ſay ſo your unkind miſtruſt of me, of what I have told you. By all the hopes I have of fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Proſperity (purſu'd ſhe) you are the Man. How can you be aſſur'd of that, Sir! (ſaid <hi>Polydor.</hi>) I am abſolutely Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:153254:16"/>
aſſur'd and dare ſwear it <hi>(replyed ſhe)</hi> For, ſhe ſee's with my Eyes, hears with my Ears, Underſtands with my In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectuals, and thinks as I do. On my word, Sir, (ſaid <hi>Polydor</hi>) you are a very dangerous Rival then.</p>
            <p>Alas, Sir, (replyed <hi>Ariadne</hi>) were I your Rival; you have a great deal the advantage in your Weapon: And the Combat would be more Pleaſant than Fatal. But be confident (continu'd ſhe) you need fear no Rival, to my certain knowledge, ſhe is paſſionately in Love with you: And to confeſs the truth, I was ſent to obſerve your motions, and if poſſible to fix you ſo long as to make this diſcourſe to you, with ſome overtures which yet I have omitted. <hi>Polydor</hi> all this time regarded her ſo earneſtly, and ſo ſtrictly ſurveyed her all over, that he hardly was ſenſible when ſhe came to this laſt Period: But at length Recol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting himſelf, Sir (ſaid he) allowing all this to be real; yet you are to learn the Circumſtances, which at preſent I am under. But forgive me, after all the ſerious Faces you have us'd, and after all
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:153254:17"/>
your earneſt diſcourſe, I am ſtill ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of my own Merits, tho (perhaps) not of your ſincerity, and the aſſurance you have from her. And come continu'd he drinking to <hi>Miranda</hi>) my Service to you, Sir. Help me I beſeech you to Divert this Gentleman's Melancholly. —Melancholly! (ſaid <hi>Ariadne</hi> very eagerly, aſſoon as ever he had ſet down the Glaſs) 'Tis you that Impoſe now, for I ſee you are about to perſwade me that I am a little civilly Diſtracted, or ſo. — But (purſu'd ſhe vehemently) pray (Sir) let us learn thoſe Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of yours which we are yet igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of. <hi>Polydor</hi> ſeeing her ſomewhat concern'd, did not know what Judgment to make of what he had heard, whether it were Real or Fictitious. But weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deliberately the Meen, the Habit, Beauty, and Diſcourſe of the Perſon, began tacitely to accuſe himſelf of Inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility to a Perſon who at the firſt ſight had offer'd him ſo conſiderable a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, as Thirty or Forty Guinneys might ha' done him, had he accepted 'em, wherefore he concluded himſelf
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:153254:17"/>
miſtaken and rather the madder of the two; which oblig'd him very eaſily and modeſtly to reply; Sir, I moſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligiouſly beg your Pardon for my own Madneſs in miſtaking you ſo long; and that you may the more eaſily be Invited to ſo generous an Act I will tell you my Circumſtances, and you will find what neceſſity I had to deſpair of my own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts in ſo great an advantage as this might ha' been to me. You may (hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily) have heard of my name (purſu'd he) if you do not know any of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, which I dare ſay is honeſt and not altogether Ignoble; my Father (let me ſpeak it with Modeſty) enjoys a plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Eſtate, Heaven be praiſed! However I am the youngeſt Son: And my For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune is ſmall enough. I have no depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance but on Providence and my own endeavours, if I ſhou'd extravagantly continue to impair that little Eſtate my Grandfather left me; and already the better moiety is engag'd, part of which you ſaw me juſt now make my laſt ſtake in this Houſe; yet, give me leave to add, I am an Honeſt Follow, true to my
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:153254:18"/>
King, and my Miſtreſs when ever I had one; no more a Gameſter than my An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors, which (may be) was too much; I mean tho, not fond of it, but in hopes to improve the little pittance was left to ſupport this Tenement, too little for the unruly Gueſt that fills it; for certainly I had never been ſo unadvis'd as to hazard my Eſtate, had it been any thing propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable to my Humour; but at preſent I only poſſeſs 80 Pounds a year, the Remainder of 150<abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> a year left me by the old Gentlemean I ſpoke of before. And now (Sir) if after all I have diſcover'd to you 'tis poſſible this Lady ſhould love me, ſhe is a Prodigy of Goodneſs: But I hope, you are convinc'd ſhe cannnot. So far I am from being convinc'd that ſhe ſhou'd not love you for your ſlender for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes (anſwered <hi>Ariadne</hi>) that it the more Confirms me you only muſt be the Man. For, theſe are the very Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances ſhe could have wiſh'd to have met with in him ſhe Lov'd; And when her Brother has told her ſhe would ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time or other throw her ſelf away, (as he call'd it) on ſome younger Brother,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:153254:18"/>
or Extravagant Elder Brother; I have often heard her proteſt, ſhe had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther beſtow her ſelf according to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts of the Perſon, not his Land, ſince ſhe bad enough to maintain both him, her ſelf and her Children ſplendidly, without being oblig'd to any of her Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations. This I dare ſafely avow (inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted <hi>Miranda</hi>) I have ſeveral times heard her declare it. Ay—But Sir, (ſaid <hi>Polydor</hi>) what a pretty Life muſt that Husband have; when on the leaſt difference imaginable the Lady Wife ſhall fly out to this Effect; <hi>Baſe Man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> do you conſider who rais'd you? God made you 'tis true; but he left you poor; I found you ſo and made you Rich?</hi> And ſuppoſe that by the advantage of her Forte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es he ſhou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d be prefer'd at Court; —<hi>Was i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not I? Was it not through my means you are what you are? Was it not my Money Brib'd ſuch a Lord? — Alas poor Thing Thou coud'ſt hardly ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> gone thither in a</hi> Hackney-Coach, <hi>much loſs in a Coach of thine own, but that I taking pity on thy thin Shoos, gave thee Room in mine; nay more, in my Bed: More miſerable
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:153254:19"/>
wretch; more C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſed Fool I! O damn'd Infatuated.</hi> — Hold, Sir, Hold! (cry'd <hi>Ariadne</hi> aloud) and almoſt out of Breath, or I ſhall burſt my Spleen and Ribs with La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ghing. Methinks you act it very naturally; y' are ſtrangely concern'd what ever's the matter: But give me the opportunity to Breath a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle; and I will tell you, ſhe is a Lady, if not of ſo good a Family as <hi>Polydor</hi>'s; yet he ſhou'd have no cauſe to bluſh at the alliance he may have, if he pleaſes. And ſince we do ſuppoſe her ſuch; we may preſume ſhe has had ſuch Education as wou'd not allow the leaſt diſobedient Word to the Man whom ſhe had once found in her Heart to Marry. And pray let me confirm you in this Opinion of her: But above all (continued ſhe) be abſolutely ſatisfied ſhe Loves you perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly. This I muſt urge too (ſaid <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randa.</hi>) I am extreamly oblig'd to the Lady (reply'd <hi>Polydor</hi>) But what does ſhe expect of me? Reciprocal Love (anſwer'd <hi>Ariadne.</hi>) If you can find in your Heart (ſaid <hi>Miranda</hi>) to caſt your ſelf away on a moſt Beautiful,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:153254:19"/>
Young, Good Humour'd, Vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tuous, Well-educated Lady, with a good For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, and one that has a great deal of Love in ſtore for you; ſay the Word, and you both may be happy. How now (interrupted <hi>Ariadne</hi>) I believe Couſin, you are in Love with her your ſelf!— But come, Sir, (continu'd ſhe A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing her ſelf to <hi>Polydor</hi>) your Anſwer? When I ſee the Lady and have diſcours'd her a while I'le reſolve you (ſaid <hi>Polydor</hi>) for (continu'd he) I hope you are not ſo unreaſonable as to propoſe to your ſelf that I ſhou'd make you any promiſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that. Still you are ſcrupulous I ſee Sir (ſaid <hi>Ariadne</hi>) and let me tell you without a Cauſe: Dare not you take my Word? You know my Name by this time I ſuppoſe, and ſome of our Family (perhaps) if not — Or if I do (interrupted <hi>Polydor</hi>) I muſt ſtill deſire to ſpeak with the Lady firſt; otherwiſe I ſhould deny my ſelf the uſe of my Reaſon; and that I beg you wou'd not exact of me. I confeſs (reply'd <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riadne</hi>) that which you ask is but reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, but ſuch is the Caprice of this
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:153254:20"/>
Lady's Humour, that ſhe is reſolv'd the Perſon ſhe deſigns for her Husband ſhall not ſee her Face till after they are Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried. And in ſhort, this is the hazard you muſt run: Conſider on't! To Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row till Eleven in the Morning is the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Minute ſhe will expect you. You'l find her in the Park by <hi>Roſamond</hi>'s Pond, accompanied only with one Lady more, both Maſqu'd. She that gives you her Hand is yours for ever. Theſe are hard Terms you'l ſay; But Remember, <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing venture, nothing have.</hi> Ay, Sir, (interrupted <hi>Polydor</hi>) or faint heart, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> No matter for the reſt. — But pray give me leave to tell you, I hazard all the little Eſtate I have: Beſides, perhaps, my Reputation, as 'tis not impoſſible but ſhe may have lov'd before to my coſt, ſhou'd I Marry her, and then my Quiet follows my Reputation, or pray Sir pardon me I beſeech you, for you may remember too, 'T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s good to look be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we leap; I muſt urge what I can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you to ſatisfie my ſelf; ſhe may, inſtead of being ſo great a Fortune, prove a greater Cheat, and Marry me to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:153254:20"/>
keep her ſelf out of a Priſon.—Hold Sir (interrupted <hi>Ariadne</hi>) have I been all this while labouring to perſwade you of her Vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tue and Wealth to ſo little pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe! What do you ſee in me that ſhou'd make you ſuſpect the truth of what I have told you, after all the Proteſtations I have made! if ſhe were a lewd Woman, or one who wanted an Husband to go to Goal for her; are there not a now in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior to you every way, that m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght act ſuch a part? in fine, Credit me; I am ſure you may be very happy with her if you embrace the Propoſals I have made you.</p>
            <p>I am in earneſt, think well on't! This is the laſt time of asking. 'Tis ſome what a ſhort warning ſhe gives a Man; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks (continu'd <hi>Polydor</hi>) ſhe might enlarge the Bounds of her Reſolution a day or two more. For, ſhe will other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe have but lit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le Reaſon to commend my Diſcretion. No matter; ſhe is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſufficiently ſatisfy'd of all your good Qual<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ties. And ſhe can't afford you one Second more. Nay (ſaid <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randa</hi>) I know her ſo well, that I dare
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:153254:21"/>
engage ſhe will not yield you one Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Shee's very determinate then in her purpoſes! (ſayd <hi>Polydor;</hi>) But me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks continu'd he) I Dream. No, <hi>Polydor,</hi> (ſaid <hi>Ariadne</hi>) you wake: But you ſhut your eyes to your own good Fortune. Open 'em I beg you. I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, you may know or have heard of her Brother Sir <hi>Fr. Heartwell,</hi> enquire at his Lodgings of his Siſter <hi>Ariadne,</hi> and if you find what I have told falſe concerning her Eſtate and Virtue, ee'n go back again to drink or to play as your Humour ſhall then ſerve you. That's pretty fair (ſaid <hi>Polydor:</hi>) But if ſhe be indeed Siſter to Sir <hi>Francis,</hi> whom I am very well acquainted with, why mayn't I ſee her before we Marry. No more Queſtions of that nature, Dear Infidel, (ſaid ſhe) I have partly told you the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagance of her Humour, and one Caution more I am to give you; If you diſcourſe one Syllable of what has paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed between us to her Brother; you loſe her for ever. To Morrow Morning you may ſatisfy your Scrupulous Conſcience in the other matters. Well!— for once
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:153254:21"/>
(ſaid he) I may chance to truſt Fortune, at leaſt I ſhall take the pains to conſult my Pillow about it; which I hope ſhe and you will allow me to do. And all the reaſon in the World! (Reply'd <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randa.</hi>) By all means (ſaid <hi>Ariadne</hi>) ſo Sir, my Service to you, (continu'd ſhe drinking to <hi>Polydor.</hi>) This is the firſt time (ſaid <hi>Polydor</hi>) that I am like to have the Honour of Pledging you: But for my part, what with drinking before the Play and ſince, I find my ſelf pretty well to paſs. Beſides, it grows late. Well Conſider (ſaid <hi>Ariadne,</hi> pulling out a Golden Watch) 'tis now turn'd of ten; and I preſume you may be weary of our Company, which has ſo long made you uneaſy. However I would have you part with us reſolved, if poſſible, to ſee this Lady that ſo Adores you, at the time appointed. I will endeavour, (Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd he) to perſwade my ſelf, which is as much as you can deſire. So, imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately they call'd a Reckoning, which <hi>Ariadne</hi> would needs diſcharge: And then parted at the Door, <hi>Polydor</hi> walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing towards <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and <hi>Ariadne</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:153254:22"/>
took Coach with <hi>Miranda</hi> for her Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Houſe; into which they got the back way as they came Where we may leave 'em to ſhift themſelves, for I hold it not convenient to peep into Ladies Privacies. In the mean time my Friend <hi>Polydor</hi> was making Reflections on what had paſs'd; ſometimes he was for going to meet 'em, then preſently Curſing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for being ſuch a Fool as to give ear to ſo, improbable a Story as he then thought it. Staggering all the way home both in Mind and Body. At laſt he reach'd his Apartment to ſpeak Gentile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; And I think, without ſaying his Prayers, he went to Bed; where he fell faſt aſleep till next Morning, about 5 or 6. When Waking, he began afreſh to recal the laſt Nights Adventure, and the Propoſition <hi>Ariadne</hi> made to him. <hi>Ha!</hi> (ſaid he to himſelf) <hi>'Tis very odd! Yet there is ſomething in it looks very Rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> The two Sparks very Rich and Gay, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially my particular Friend whoſe Pockets were doubly lin d: That Watch, that G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> and thoſe Rings I took notice of on his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gers, were marks of no ordinary Quali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:153254:22"/>
His Meen was</hi> a la mode, <hi>Eaſy and Sweet; His Converſation Free and Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous: Sure he can have no Ends in this.</hi> —How Fool! (Replyd he to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf) is it not very poſſible he has been, and (may be) is her Gallant, who now is ſated, and would willingly turn her on my hands, with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> advantage of a Great Belly. Yet as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>rid, why might not another Man, any Raſcal might have ſerv'd his ends. What ſhall I do? I am al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready fallen a Stern very finely; and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs I meet with a good Pilot I ſhall run a' ground to rights. This Lady then muſt be my Pilot, I was mor'd before, but now I only hold at one Anchor, and that too drags too faſt. Well! I will 'een throw at all. Saying ſo, he was juſt going to leap out o' Bed; when a ſecond and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Thought ſurpris'd him and threw him again on his Pillow. <hi>What art a' going to do—Fool</hi> (cry'd he to himſelf) <hi>See all thy old Acquaintance ſome of 'em Witty, Satyrical Rogues, others Da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n'd, Dull Dogs, all of them Barking at thee aloud; Is this the Spark we have ſo long miſtaken for a Man of Senſe! Is this he
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:153254:23"/>
who was wont to help us Laugh at all thoſe Sots that durſt hazard their Carkaſſes with one Woman for better for worſe? And is this</hi> Jolly Debauche <hi>at laſt overtaken? Nay more, Jilted by a Lewd Woman, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Heireſs? Very fine i' faith! — No, no, I'le ha' none on't; I ſhall hardly give 'em the Opportunity to eaſe their Spleens at my coſt.</hi> — Yet— (conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nu'd he, turning on t' other ſide;) My little, new Acquaintance did urge what he ſaid ſo vehemently, and with ſo much concern; that I muſt believe him.— Well—Hang't. The Die is thrown, and it is Decreed. At theſe Words out he jump'd, as reſolutely as <hi>Caeſar</hi> into the <hi>Rubicon:</hi> Makes himſelf as fine as the beſt of three good Suits could make him! Puts all the Guineys he cou'd then come at in his Pockets, which I think were juſt three. Then down he drops on his Knees, lifting up his Hands and Eyes; but where his Heart was at that time I will not pretend to determin. Well! —At length up he gets, and out o' doors he marches very courageouſly to Sir <hi>Francis</hi>'s, where he met juſt coming
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:153254:23"/>
out, one of his Acquaintance who was very intimate with our young Knight. <hi>O</hi> Jack (ſaid he aſſoon as he ſaw him) <hi>you are the only Man I cou'd wiſh to have encountr'd! And, if you are not buſy we muſt drink one Bottle this Morning.</hi> I am no Morning drinker (ſaid his Friend) However, to wait on you, I don't much care if I take one Glaſs, provided the Wine be good. Where will you go? The blue Poſts in the <hi>Hay market</hi> I think is the neareſt place where we may ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture our Carkaſſes (anſwered <hi>Polydor.</hi>) Now, I really believe he was in the right on't: For, he had an excellent Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late for <hi>French</hi> Wines; I dare aſſure you: And I wou'd aſſoon take his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of 'em as any Man's I know. To the blue Poſts then they went. Where, after they had each of 'em drank their two Glaſſes a piece; <hi>Polydor</hi> began to inform himſelf of <hi>Ariadnes</hi> Fortune and Humour, which he found anſwerable to the Character ſhe had given him of her ſelf the Night paſt in every particular. The Gentleman who gave him this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count did ſo enlarge on her Beauty and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:153254:24"/>
Gayety of Humour, that <hi>Polydor</hi> began to be Jealous, he lov'd her himſelf: Which made 'em part the ſooner by a Bottle or two. <hi>Polydor</hi> now long'd for Eleven a' Clock, being perfectly reſolv'd for once to make a blind Bargain with Fortune, and wholly Committed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to her Guidance. I think, 't was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Nine and Ten when he ſhook off his Friend; ſo he went directly to the Park where he expected <hi>Ariadne</hi> as ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerly as if he had Lov'd her for ſeven years together, and that the firſt time ſhe had ever made him an Aſſignation. I can but think what Reflections he made on his Friends Relation of <hi>Ariadne</hi>'s Perſon, Beautiful (ſaid he) to a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle and of an Humour as extravagant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Pleaſant. Is ſhe ſo, Sir (ſaid <hi>Polydor</hi> to himſelf as he walk'd) ſo much the more happy is your Friend and <hi>Polydor</hi> like to be. Little doſt thou think Dear Heart (continu'd he) that I am going to be Marry'd with her this very Morning. And 'gad 'tis her own fault too. If ſhe will throw away her ſelf and her Eſtate on an Honeſt Fellow of a younger Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:153254:24"/>
who can help it! The Devil take them that wou'd hinder her for me. I ſpeak nothing but Reaſon, I am ſure. I think it is fit ſhe ſhou'd have her Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour. Shee's like to pay for't, I believe. He told me too, ſhe Sung finely. That's another excellence I mightily well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of. We may make ſhift to Sing two parts I fancy. Let me ſee! what new Song have <hi>I</hi> to Surprize her with! <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mante Douce,</hi> &amp;c.— Dam theſe <hi>French</hi> Songs! No <hi>I'le</hi> Entertain her with plain down right <hi>Engliſh.</hi> As thus (ſaid he humming it ſoftly to himſelf.)</p>
            <q>
               <l>Tho' your Pride be great as your Beauty,</l>
               <l>And my Vows you hear with ſcorn;</l>
               <l>Yet (Alas!) 'tis but my Duty</l>
               <l>Silently to Love and Mourn.</l>
               <l>In hopeleſs Anguiſh</l>
               <l>I'd chuſe to Languiſh,</l>
               <l>Rather than wiſh to break the Chain;</l>
               <l>'Tis more Glory</l>
               <l>Thus to Adore y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>Than 'ore all your Sex to Reign!</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:153254:25"/>Pox on't! (ſaid he) <hi>I</hi> made theſe Words my ſelf to a <hi>French</hi> Air; <hi>I</hi> don't know whether ſhee'l like 'em or no. But ſhee muſt take 'em for better or worſe, as <hi>I</hi> take her. By this time he found him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf at the farther end of the Wall; <hi>I</hi> mean that end toward the Mulberry Garden that was. There <hi>I</hi> ſay, he found himſelf; for he was abſolutely loſt before in the Contemplation of his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes Perfections. Onward he goes to <hi>Roſamond</hi>'s Pond, where he no ſooner Arriv'd, but he was Surpriz'd at the ſight of two Ladies in their Dreſs, Maſqu'd. One of which, who, by the Richneſs of her Cloaths ſeem'd to be of the better Quality of the two, preſented him a moſt Beautiful, Soft, White Hand; without ſaying one Word to him. He took it, and ſeeting one Knee to the Ground, kiſs'd it moſt religiouſly. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve you may ſee the print of his Lips there yet, if ſhe has not us'd ſome art to get it out. Well—he look'd on it, and kiſs'd it, and kiſs'd it, and look'd on it again: Then gaz'd on her two De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:153254:25"/>
Charming, Black Eyes through the peep holes of her Mask. And fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy'd to himſelf a Face, if not ſo Beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful altogether as <hi>Ariadnes</hi> indeed was; yet ſuch as the moſt excellent Painter cou'd not have flatter'd if he ſhou'd en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour it. The other Lady was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what the Kinder of the two; for, ſeeing him ſtare thus Silently and Curiouſly, ſhe pull'd of her Mask and ask'd him if he had never a Tongue to praiſe what he beheld? No, Madam, (ſaid he) not you your ſelf neither, ſo much, as it deſerves; though you come ſo near the excellencies of an Angel. For, to give her her due; ſhe was as Beautiful as any of the Sex, except <hi>Ariadne;</hi> for, I muſt maintain the Character of my He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roin, for a Reaſon that I know. But ſtill, —I ſay give the Devil his due! Well. She was very handſom, and there's an end on't. Nay <hi>Polydor</hi> (ſaid <hi>Ariadne</hi> keeping her Mask on) we know you are a Courtier. But 'tis a little odd (methinks) that you ſhou'd ſo highly commend what you have not as yet ſeen. How do you know now (conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:153254:26"/>
ſhe) but this Mask covers the moſt ugly Face you ever ſaw! O 'tis impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, Madam, (ſaid <hi>Polydor</hi> in a Rapture) 'tis impoſſible, I ſwear, with thoſe eyes. But how can you tell (ſaid <hi>Ariadne</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupting him) but the Skin on't may be as black as the Velvet of my Mask. I believe it is as ſoft (ſaid he very Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly, feeling on the Mask) But Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don me (Madam) your Eyelids have confirm'd the contrary. I have ſeen, Madam (continu'd he) enough to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat your Victory. Diſpoſe, Madam, (purſu'd he all over in a tranſport of Love!) Diſpoſe how you pleaſe of your Slave. I was an Infidel laſt Night, 'tis true, but now I will believe, nay I do believe you are the greateſt Bleſſing Heav'n cou'd beſtow on me in this World.</p>
            <p>Hey day! What a hopeful and ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain change is here, (cry'd <hi>Ariadne</hi>) ſure this is not the ſame <hi>Polydor</hi> my Couſin ſaw laſt Night. No, no Madam, (ſaid he) not a Word of that over Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, Scrupulous, and Ill natur'd Fellow. I have not one doubt about me: You
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:153254:26"/>
appear to me all Glorious and Good. But we trifle, (Madam) Let us walk to the other end of the Park and take Coach for <hi>Mary Bone.</hi> Hold, Sir, (ſaid ſhe) there's a Coach waits us at this Gate; which, I preſume, is as convenient. O moſt advantageous (ſaid <hi>Polydor,</hi> lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her towards the Gate) where they quickly Arriv'd, and got into the Coach; which made all the reaſonable haſt to the Bowling Green that cou'd be expected. Cry your Mercy, I mean to the Church. But I had been oftner at the firſt, which made it come ſooner into my Thoughts.</p>
            <p>Beſides I had forgot <hi>Polydor</hi> had any Buſineſs at the laſt mention'd place, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he has had at the Green. By the way, (ſaid <hi>Ariadne</hi> to him) have you bethought your ſelf of a Ring? A Ring Child? (ſaid he) no, faith.— But by good Fortune here is one on my Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger which a <hi>French</hi> Miſtreſs of mine gave me at <hi>Paris;</hi> and we may make ſhift for once with it. Nay, nay, (ſaid ſhe) ſhift now and ſhift always. But come, it muſt and ſhall do. But hark you (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinu'd ſhe) don't you fancy we go as
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:153254:27"/>
merrily to Execution as any two Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd People ever did? You may call it what you will (ſaid he) but (methinks) 'twas a little improperly ſpoken. Was it ever ſaid a Man was Condemn'd to be happy? For ſuch I apprehend my Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance at the preſent; I don't know what you judge of your own. O (ſaid ſhe) doubt not, I have as good an Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of you as you can have of me, for the Heart of you. I ſee then (interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Miranda</hi>) you are both in a fair way to be perfectly happy. — You know I muſt make her ſpeak ſomething, and not let her ſit like a Mute all the while; much contrary to the humour of her Sex. Well—But— now or about this time they got within ſight of the Steeple, Look there <hi>Polydor</hi> (ſaid <hi>Ariadne</hi>) what do you think of turning back? Why (ſaid he) I think of it as of the only thing I muſt deny you at the preſent. No, no—(continu'd he) I am reſolv'd to enter the Enchanted Caſtle with thee, and try the force of it's Charms. Ten to one interrupted <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adne</hi>) you may find 'em too ſtrong for
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:153254:27"/>
you at a long Run. But for my part (ſhe purſu'd) I am as Reſolute as my Friend <hi>John Florio.</hi> And ſo (ſaid ſhe) Coach-Man open the Door. They all three immediately lighted and went directly toward the Church; juſt before they came to the Porch, a little dapper old Fellow comes to 'em; and asks 'em, if they had any buſineſs with him this Morning. Why faith Friend (ſaid <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lydor</hi>) if you can mumble over the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony, or ſo—We have— How! (interrupted <hi>Ariadne</hi>) mumble it over! No don't you miſtake! <hi>I</hi> mean to have it as Audibly, Diſtinctly, Laudably, and Plainly read, as ever <hi>I</hi> have heard part ſpoken on the Stage: But you are in the right on't <hi>Polydor</hi> (continu'd ſhe) for this Right Reverend looks as if he cou'd only mumble it. Well; Madam, (ſaid the little Old Gentleman) <hi>I</hi> can make a ſhift to <hi>ſay Amen</hi> plain enough <hi>I</hi> warrant you. But Mr. — the Miniſter is within — And <hi>I</hi> believe at leiſure by this time to do you that Office which he has dont this Morning to four Couple more. —But, believe me Gentlefolks you are
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:153254:28"/>
the fineſt we have ſeen today. O! We thank you, Sir, (ſaid <hi>Polydor</hi>) But pray how long do you Ply here a Days? Ply here Sir! (ſaid he) we expect Company here generally from Six till Twelve. — But ſee, Sir, (continu'd he) the laſt Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are juſt coming out! I have a little buſineſs with 'em, e'r they go. If you pleaſe to walk up to the Altar, I'l wait on you before you have done your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements to the Miniſter.— O! your Servant, good Sir; we don't doubt it (ſaid <hi>Polydor,</hi> leading <hi>Ariadne</hi> to the Fatal place:) There <hi>Polydor</hi> immediately opens their Caſe, diſcovers their Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, and asks a Remedy; Promiſing him to reward him like a Gentleman. <hi>And now</hi> (continu'd he, addreſſing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to <hi>Ariadne</hi> very Obediently and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morouſly as cou'd be expected from any Man in his Circumſtances) <hi>Now I hope you will diſcover thoſe Perfections which yet I only Adore in Idea's too Imperfect to be call'd the true Shadows of 'em.</hi> How do you mean? (ſaid ſhe.) <hi>I mean</hi> (an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd he) <hi>This Cloud muſt be remov'd that I may behold the Sun. — In ſhort,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:153254:28"/>
Madam, this Mask muſt off.</hi> — She was very unwilling to unmask, but the Miniſter urging the neceſſity of it, ſhe was at laſt oblig'd to conform. <hi>Polydor</hi> at the ſight of her Beauty ſtood like a Statue, and was all over Extaſy'd with the Apprehenſion of his future Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. But at length recollecting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, he wou'd fain have knelt to kiſs her Hand, but ſhe prevented him, Charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to forbear expreſſing his Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Love, or any other Paſſion, till the Ceremony was over, and they in a more convenient place: It laſted not long in the performance, but the Effects I think remain to this day.</p>
            <p>After the laſt <hi>Amen,</hi> having before gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>v'n the Parſon a Guinney, and the Clerk and Sexton another, out of which they were to diſtribute half a Piece to the Poor, (for he was a mighty kind-heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Soul as liv'd, to my knowledge.) Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all this I ſay, and 'tis true, they took Coach, and drave back to <hi>Lockets,</hi> where, by the deſire of <hi>Ariadne, Polydor</hi> beſpoke two or three pretty ſeaſonable Diſhes of Meat: And return'd in all haſt to ſay all
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:153254:29"/>
the moſt obliging and tender things his Soul was capable of uttering.</p>
            <p>Firſt he threw himſelf at her Feet, Embrac'd her Knees, kiſſing her Hands by force, and almoſt wept with Joy. Then on a ſuddain up he ſtarts, and like a meer Tyrant in Love, falls aboard her delicate powting Lip, and Lovely Riſing Breaſts, without ſo much as giving her the opportunity to chide him. <hi>Hold— Hold</hi> Polydor (ſaid ſhe at laſt) <hi>I muſt make Articles with you. Hear me I charge you. For this day is all mine, tho it be the laſt I muſt command in.</hi>— O! ſay not ſo my Soul (ſaid he almoſt out of Breath) Thou ſhalt ever command me.— Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve then (ſaid <hi>Ariadne</hi>)—If you will ſit quietly by me, and once in a quarter of an Hour kiſs me; I will now force my ſelf this firſt time to kiſs a Man.—Ah (ſaid <hi>Polydor</hi> looking on her very Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly) tho your Condition be ſomewhat ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d; yet for the Bleſſing of a Kiſs gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven me heartily by you; I will forbear as much as Fleſh and Blood can. Stand fair then (ſaid ſhe) and look on <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randa.</hi> O I beg your Pardon (cry'd
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:153254:29"/>
               <hi>Polydor</hi>) I ſhall loſe the ſatisfaction of encountring your Eyes then; which is above half the pleaſure of your Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; tho I cou'd eaſily be perſwaded to look that way, were not <hi>Ariadne</hi> here. Well then (ſaid ſhe ſmiling and bluſhing at the ſame time) I'le ſhut my Eyes. O that's cruel (cry'd <hi>Miranda:</hi>) No, no, fair play ought to be, Couſin: Come Advance, and do't as you ſhou'd! Can you Inſtruct me then? (ſaid <hi>Ariadne.</hi>) No matter, Madam, (interrupted <hi>Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor</hi>) Let Love inſtruct you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Well! Have at you then</hi> (cry'd ſhe throwing her Arms about his Neck, and ſhedding Tears which I ought to have call'd Pearls, according to the Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable cuſtom of other Writers: But theſe were only Briny Tears, nothing elſe in the World; which ſhe meerly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtill'd from her Brain through exceſs of Joy, I preſume:) <hi>Now my dear</hi> Polydor (ſaid ſhe giving him a Thouſand Kiſſes) <hi>Are you now convinc'd</hi> Ariadne <hi>loves you? I am ſo well convinc'd, and ſo extreamly ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of my happineſs,</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>that I wou'd not change circumſtances with the happy and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:153254:30"/>
Amorous</hi> Mark Anthony, <hi>were he now li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving with his</hi> Cleopatra. <hi>O</hi> (ſaid ſhe, retreating a little) <hi>I muſt take care you do not ſurfeit on't. Too much will cloy you. Ah! how Cruel are you now</hi> (ſaid <hi>Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor,</hi> purſuing her) <hi>can you imagin I ſhou'd ſurfeit before I have taſted! How! Before you have taſted!</hi> (replyed <hi>Ariad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne) Why, I believe by this time you are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to diſtinguiſh the touch of my Lips, from any Ladies in Town, though in the dark, or hoodwink'd; you have already been ſo familiar with 'em. Alas</hi> Madam, (ſaid he) <hi>this is but like a Walk and a Glaſs of</hi> Rheniſh <hi>before Dinner to whet a Mans appetite. Or wou'd you have me be ſatisfy'd only with the ſmell of a Diſh of Meat that I Love? No,</hi> Madam (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinu'd he) <hi>Conſummation is the ſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al part of our buſineſs. That is yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind. I don't know what you mean by Conſummation</hi> (cry'd ſhe) <hi>But (methinks) I have already done you all the right in the World. — But</hi> (continu'd ſhe looking toward the Door) <hi>I am oblig'd to the Waiters who have juſt brought up Dinner, to prevent any farther deſcant on ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſant
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:153254:30"/>
a Subject. Come</hi> (purſu'd ſhe very eagerly) <hi>Let us ſit, I am hungry. Ay faith and ſo am I too</hi> (ſaid <hi>Polydor) and yet though Grace is ſaid and the meat ready, you won't ſo much as bring it to the Table, that I may fall on. No more Nonſenſe</hi> (interrupted <hi>Ariadne.) 'Tis here already, and you may eat if you pleaſe. Come! Let us ſit Couſin</hi> (continu'd ſhe looking on <hi>Miranda) The Gentleman (perhaps) has no Stomach yet. Gad but he has, and a ſwinging one too</hi> (ſaid <hi>Polydor;) and that you ſhall find Dear heart, e'r long.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With that he ſate him down at the left hand of <hi>Ariadne,</hi> and eat like a Souldier in a Siege: But drank little. <hi>Much good d'it you Don,</hi> (ſaid <hi>Ariadne) you are welcome to our</hi> Engliſh <hi>Fleſh; I fear you have but little on't i' your Countrey: For, to ſay truth, and ſpeak plain</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh, <hi>you feed like a Farmer. I thank you,</hi> (Madam ſaid he, with his Mouth full, and looking another way) <hi>ſo me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks. But</hi> (continu'd he, pulling of his Peruke) <hi>you ſhall have better proofs of my eating e'r</hi> I <hi>ha' done yet. Hold!
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:153254:31"/>
Good Sir!</hi> (cry'd <hi>Miranda) pray keep on your Perurke, or I fear we muſt beſpeak another Diſh. You may beſpeak a dozen more if you pleaſe Madam,</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>but I'm afraid you are like to find none of the effects of my eating. No, nor any body elſe but your ſelf I fancy</hi> (ſaid <hi>Ariadne.) That's as time ſhall try, ſweet heart,</hi> (ſaid <hi>Polydor) But — you may chance to Groan for it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ariadne</hi> cou'd not chuſe but Laugh down right to hear him talk and ſee him eat ſo heartily. And I believe ſhe was well enough pleaſed with his Stomach; for ſome reaſon that ſhall be kept ſecret at this time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But pray Sir</hi> (ſaid ſhe Laughing) <hi>Do you always eat thus? Always Honey!</hi> (replied <hi>Polydor) Ay: I think I do Child. What then? Why, nothing, (ſaid ſhe) but only I think it moſt convenient we ſhou'd go live in</hi> Wales, <hi>or in ſome other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, where Meat is cheaper than it is here, or you'l eat us out of Houſe and Home. — Nay-gad</hi> (ſaid he, looking a little ſurly) <hi>you need not grudge me my Victuals, for you are like to reap the benefit on't. I thank you Sir</hi> (replyed <hi>Ariadne) But I
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:153254:31"/>
don't care for't at ſecond hand. Lord!</hi> (cry'd <hi>Polydor</hi> lifting up his Hands and Eyes) <hi>what a delicate reaſonable Wife have I got! I warrant</hi> (continu d he looking pleaſantly on <hi>Ariadne) you could be ſatisfy'd barely with Kiſſing, Eating, and Drinking with me. Nay, I can't tell that,</hi> (ſaid ſhe) <hi>But</hi> I <hi>ſee you are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding againſt the worſt. No, no, Dear Heart</hi> (cry'd <hi>Polydor,</hi> tranſported with Joy) <hi>for the beſt, for the beſt</hi> Ariadne! <hi>Nay,</hi> (ſaid ſhe) I <hi>know ne'r another of the Name beſides my ſelf, and if all theſe pains be taken, for me,</hi> I <hi>am much oblig'd to you: for (methinks) you ſweat at it! I ſhall before we ha' done</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>no doubt. Thus did they eat and talk till they were weary of both.</hi> The Cloth was taken away, and the Glaſs went round merrily as long as one Bottle laſted. Then fell <hi>Polydor</hi> to kiſſing again: Till he made both himſelf and his Lady mad: And I'm afraid he did not a little diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oblige <hi>Miranda;</hi> who was fain to go humming about the Room to divert the Thoughts that ſometimes did Aſſault her.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:153254:32"/>
               <hi>Well now</hi> (cry'd Ariadne) <hi>I ſwear I can endure no longer! Pray ſit farther, and let us parley a little. — You may remember</hi> (continued he) <hi>you gave me a Ring to day. Ay</hi> (ſaid he,) <hi>I fancy I did, what of that? Only I mean to return your kindneſs</hi> (ſaid ſhe) pulling of a Rich Diamond-Ring of her finger) <hi>pray wear this for my ſake,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now (continued ſhe) I muſt beg you would Entertain your ſelf with the Bottle till our Return; for my Coſin and I muſt be private for a Minute or two: And that you may not altogether be Drinking, pray take the pains to tell over this Gold, (ſaid ſhe throwing a Purſe full on the Table) There ſhould be a Hundred peices: See (Sir,) Your Servant for a time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nay, nay,</hi> ſaid <hi>Polydor, I like the Employment pretty well, ſince I muſt be rob'd of thy dear Company ſo long as theſe two Minutes.</hi> Good <hi>Sir,</hi> (ſaid <hi>Miranda</hi>) don't be Jealous, I'le be your <hi>Argus.</hi> If I thought my <hi>Ariadne</hi> needed Watching, replied he, I would e'en leave her to the wide World; And
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:153254:32"/>
her own Roving humour. This he ſpoke Kiſſing her, ſhe dropt him a Curſey and out ſhe went with <hi>Miranda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He preſently fell to telling the Broad peices, which he found exact y an Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred in Number: He put them up very carefully, and laid them again on the Table: And took a March three or four times about the Room. At laſt he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought himſelf, and takes to the Bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle. <hi>Well honeſt Polydor,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>her's to thee: Thy dear Ariadnes good health. But I gad methinks ſhe ſtays ſweetly.</hi> He drank off his glaſs, and expected almoſt a quarter of an hour longer with indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Patience. But ſeeing no <hi>Ariad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne</hi> come yet, he called up a Waiter, and asked him, where the two Ladies were, that went down about half an hour ago? <hi>They took Coach Sir,</hi> ſaid the Waiter, <hi>aſſoon as they left you: Why 'tis Impoſſible. Thou art Drunk ſure!</hi> Saying ſo: He took up the Gold in all haſt, and ran down to the Bar to be more fully ſatisfied of his Misfortune; which he was too ſoon. He ran up into the Room again, like a man di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:153254:33"/>
where he ſhut the Door to himſelf, and fell a railing at all Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men kind, <hi>What! fitted thus,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>'tis very deviliſh: What a dam'd Sot was I to l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t her go! But rather what an Eternal Coxcomb to Marry ſuch a Jilt! This is no more</hi> Ariadne, <hi>I warrant, than</hi> I <hi>am</hi> Ariadne. <hi>'Tis impoſſible a Perſon of her Quality and Education ſhould be guilty of ſo lewd an Action! Where the Devil ſhould ſhe go! Or what Buſineſs had ſhe, but with me! I find I am meerly drawn into a Priſon: Ay, ay, ſhee's in Debt, i'le lay my Life on it, and I muſt ſuffer the weight of all the Actions that are laid againſt her. — So, hey for a Priſon! But may ſhe not happily be gone to her Brothers? Then ſhall I look on my ſelf as a raſh, Jealous Fop. Well</hi> (continued he) <hi>I am reſolved i'le ſee.</hi> Immediately upon this thought, he flies down Stairs, calls for a Bill, but he was anſwered, 'twas all paid. <hi>Paid, Ha! marry</hi> (ſaid he to himſelf) <hi>I like the Matter the better for this. Come, come! Chear up my Heart! All may be well yet.</hi> He call d preſently for a Coach, and on
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:153254:33"/>
he drives to Sir <hi>Francis's:</hi> but juſt as he came near the Houſe, his Courage fail'd him, and he was ſet down within five or ſix doors of it. He ſtood ſtill ſometime conſidering what he ſhould do, whether it were Convenient to go directly thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and ask for her, or to pretend a Viſit to her Brother, and ſo learn in diſcourſe, what was become of <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adne.</hi> But at laſt, he bethought himſelf of a better Expedient: He knocked at the door, and asked if his Friend were there, with whom he drank in the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. The Footman that opened the door told him, he was juſt riſen from Dinner with Sir <hi>Francis: Prithee, then tell him</hi> (ſaid Polydor) <hi>I would ſpeak with him here.</hi> The Footman did ſo, and preſently led him to <hi>Polydor. O my dear Friend</hi> (ſaid <hi>Polydor</hi> with a great deal of Concern) <hi>I muſt needs drink a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Bottle with you this Minute; you ſhall not deny me: I am ſo very Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholly and out of humour, that you will be very unkind if you do. Well</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>I'le but juſt make my</hi> baiſe les mains <hi>to</hi> Sir <hi>Francis, and ſtay one half hour with
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:153254:34"/>
you:</hi> He juſt went in and return'd to his perplex'd Friend. They went to the ſame Houſe again, where they drank their Mornings Draught together: And <hi>Polydor</hi> began his Circumlocutions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he came to the buſineſs. <hi>Dear Friend</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>how happy am I to meet thee again at a time when</hi> I <hi>ſtood in moſt need of thy Company:</hi> I <hi>have met with un untoward Accident ſince</hi> I <hi>left thee; which has. ſo diſturb'd me</hi> I <hi>cannot yet Compoſe my ſelf. But come!</hi> (continu'd he) <hi>Help me to divert the thought on't. Let's drink and talk of things indifferent! When ſaw you the Beautiful</hi> Ariadne <hi>whom you ſo lowdly commended in the Morning? Not ſince laſt Night</hi> (anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his Friend) <hi>ſhe went out o' Town this Morning before ſeven a' Clock as far as St.</hi> Albans, <hi>to a Couſin of hers who is taken deſperately ill; one whom ſhe loves moſt dearly. Sir</hi> Francis <hi>went with her himſelf as far as</hi> High-Gate: <hi>She had an Hack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney-Coach and four Horſes that waited on her thither empty, till ſhe left her Brother. Ha!</hi> (ſaid <hi>Polydor) does ſhe go often out of Town, has ſhe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:153254:34"/>
ſuch frequent Excurſions, She's hardly at Home</hi> (reply'd his Friend) <hi>three days in a Week together. A pretty ſort of a Lady</hi> (cry'd Polydor:) <hi>Is it a he Couſin, or a ſhe Couſin, ſhe's gone to Viſit? A very pretty Lady 'tis ile aſſure you</hi> (ſaid he.) <hi>Why doſt not thou ſtrike in with this ſame</hi> Ariadne, <hi>or with ſome of her fine Couſins?</hi> (ſaid Polydor.) <hi>O ſhe's too great for me! Beſides ſhe has been engaged to a Perſon of very conſiderable Quality a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove theſe three Months.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O Curſed Jealouſie! A hopeful Spark, and a kind Friend indeed was this ſame <hi>Marwood</hi> to <hi>Polydor!</hi> Now ſhe was no more Engaged than her Monkey. Only he loved her himſelf, and ſpoke this leaſt his Friend ſhould have any thoughts of attempting her. And indeed he ſaid enough to make <hi>Polydor</hi> mad, and to confirm him in the opinion that he had Married a Cheat inſtead of an Heireſs. However, he forced himſelf to look and talk as pleaſantly as was poſſible for a Man in his Condition: till at laſt the Bottle being out, <hi>Marwood</hi> was in haſt to be
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:153254:35"/>
one to his beloved Knight, which made both part very eaſily with one another. <hi>Polydor</hi> for his part walk'd very diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſolately into the Park, to the fatal place where he firſt ſaw the <hi>falſe fair One,</hi> as he was pleaſed to call her in his Dumps. The firſt thing he reflected on was the Pond. <hi>Humb!</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſamonds Pond! What a dull Beaſt was I not to apprehend the ill Omen, in the very Name of the place where we firſt met! that ever</hi> I <hi>ſhould hope to find an honeſt Woman at a place that took its Name from a lewd Strumpet!</hi> Very fine, faith! As if it were impoſſible to encounter a good Woman there becauſe of the Name it had! When I dare ſay, I have ſeen above twenty Citizens Wives and Daughters at that very place; Nay, if I ſhould ſay forty, I ſhould not Ly. And whether they could be light or diſhoneſt, I leave all the Town to determine. Nay, more, I my ſelf have walked thither with a She kindred of my own, of about 7 or 8 years Old, but I muſt confeſs, I cannot ſwear ſhe was a Maid, yet it is not improbable but ſhe might
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:153254:35"/>
be a very good one. But now to our <hi>Hero,</hi> who all this while has been Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Pond, and Comparing himſelf to a decoy'd Du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k. <hi>Heavens!</hi> (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued he) <hi>was not the ſight of thoſe ſufficient Caution to thee, to prevent thy Ruin!</hi> Then bending his thoughts another way (he purſued) <hi>I am glad I did not Bed her: I'le ſue her to a divorce now, and ſwear point blanck ſhe ſtole me.</hi> — (Did not he talk like a Madman now!) But he ſoon recollected his ſtragling Senſes, and (cry'd) <hi>Fool that I am! was ever ſuch a thing heard of! O Death and the Devil</hi> (continued he) <hi>Whoever She be, She is Beautiful enough to tempt any man to make me a Monſter! A Cuckold! Which (perhaps) is juſt now in Agitation. — O Juſtice! Juſtice! How many of my own intimate acquaintance have I ſerved ſo! Not to name Strangers and Forreigners. — Well! I am at laſt overtaken, and now I pay for all! For all of them put together could never have made half ſuch a Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as my falſe Ariadne! My Jilting A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riadne, my Devil, Damn'd impoſtour A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riadne!
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:153254:36"/>
Yet one Comfort is</hi> (continued he looking on the Diamond Ring ſhe gave him) <hi>My Cheat is a Cheat of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity: for I am ſure this Stone is Right, and the Gold is good old Gold! Marwood ſaid Shee's gone to St.</hi> Albans; <hi>why let her go to the Devil! who would ride twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Miles to ſee himſelf made a Cuckold! Ah but</hi> (continued he) <hi>That is the true Ariadne. VVell! — True or falſe, I'le write to her. But firſt I'le go Play off ten or twenty pieces that I may write more eaſily.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this Reſolution he went to look for Company, at moſt of the Gaming Houſes in Town; and at laſt he met two or three of his Acquaintance at <hi>Baniſters</hi> in the City, where he fell to Play; And fortune, as if ſhe deſigned to make him amends for the trick ſhe plaid him ſo lately; threw every Dy to his advantage, ſo that in two Hours time, he had won above forty Guinneys: So wee'l leave him, to find what's be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of our two <hi>Ladys Errant.</hi> They were by this time gotten almoſt as far as St. <hi>Albans:</hi> for 'twas true, that her
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:153254:36"/>
Brother left her at <hi>Highgate</hi> in the Morning; but he was no ſooner out of ſight, but ſhe turned and made for St. <hi>Jameſe's,</hi> but aſſoon as ſhe came into Town, ſhe bid the Coachman take out two of the Horſes, and ſo went to meet her <hi>Polydor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, her Couſin was in as good health as I am at this preſent writing praiſed —for the ſame (as my Mothers Maid, I remember uſed to begin her Letters, when I writ them for her, about twenty years ago.) But it was a trick of <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adnes</hi> to cover her real deſign of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying that very Morning, who had counterfeited a Letter as from her Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin, whoſe hand ſhe knew perfectly well, and ſhew d it to her Brother. But (perchance) you will ask me why ſhe did not take her own Coach and Horſes to perform that Journey? for certainly that was eaſier, and looked greater! But did ever I tell you ſhe kept a Coach? yes, now you ſhall know ſhe did. However, ſhe foreſaw the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience if ſhe had met <hi>Polydor</hi> in her own Coach; and beſides her Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:153254:37"/>
would have been witneſſes of what ſhe intended to conceal, had ſhe returned to Town with them about her. And again, I believe ſhe was willing to ſpare her own Horſes. Now are you ſatisfied?</p>
            <p>As they were within two Miles of their Journeys End (ſaid <hi>Miranda</hi> to her fair Couſin) <hi>For Heavens ſake what is in your mind, that you leave your Husband the very firſt day of your Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage? I ſhould not have wondered had you left him after the Honey-moon; I mean if you had fairly taken your leave of him for a week or ſo: But this (me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks) is a little inhumane. Alas! How dull thou art my Dear!</hi> (repli'd Ariadne) <hi>I deſign to try his Patience and his Conſtancy; and all the World ſhall not diſwade me from treating him much more ſeverely yet, for ſome days: I Married him too ſoon, to be acquainted with all his Humours; but I am reſolved, I will know moſt of'em, ere we come cloſer toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And I think it is but a juſt Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment for his eaſineſs, in ſo ſoon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leiving a Stranger, in a matter of ſo
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:153254:37"/>
great Importance. I like his Addreſs and Diſcourſe well enough; nay ſo well, that I was obliged to make the more haſt from him, leſt he ſhould have made me re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of my purpoſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nay,</hi> (ſaid Miranda) <hi>I very well know the pretty innocent extravagances of your humour, and am ſenſible, you are not to be prevailed on to forbear them, eſpecially when they carry with them any ſhew of Reaſon. But</hi> (continued ſhe) <hi>how long my Dear doſt thou intend to torment him? Why — This day Sennight</hi> (reply'd A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riadne) <hi>I mean to give him my ſelf, and all that I have for Ever, and Ever, and Amen. Well be ſure you do</hi> (ſaid Miran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da) <hi>Or I'le be certain to diſcover all to him the very next day following. I give you leave</hi> (cry'd ſhe) <hi>but not a word on it before, if thou haſt any kindneſs for me. Be confident</hi> (ſaid her Couſin) <hi>I will be ſilent. Nay, 'tis your beſt way let me tell you</hi> (repli'd Ariadne) <hi>for fear I ſhould be revenged on you, and let</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood <hi>know how paſſionately you love him. You won't be ſo inhuman I hope</hi> (inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted Miranda) <hi>do you think I ſhall
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:153254:38"/>
ever be able to ſee any of our acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance again if you do? Never diſturb your ſelf</hi> (ſaid Ariadne) <hi>I only ſhew you how eaſily, and bravely I could be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged on you, if you begin firſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this time they found themſelves at the Ladys Houſe they went to Viſit, they preſently alighted and went in; where they were received with all ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable Kindneſs and Reſpect, and the more becauſe their Coming was unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, and the obligation pleaſantly ſurpriſing. Here I muſt take my leave of them, and look a little back for my friend <hi>Polydor:</hi> who that Night came off a Winner by threeſcore Guinneys, pretty well laden with Wine too, which made him ſleep that N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght the more ſoundly, (perhaps) without e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo much as dreaming on his Bride; for Wine let me tell you, is a Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Remedy againſt Love, eſpecially if the infection be but newly received: Beſides, he was a Man of a ſtrong Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, and could ſwagger it out moſt Modiſhly: yet when he gave his mind to it, could Love like a Sparrow,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:153254:38"/>
and as Conſtantly as any Turtle. In the Morning he waked between 7 and 8, for you muſt know it was paſt One ere he got into Bed: and he uſually ſlept ſix hours upon a Tack, and that che<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fly when he had been Drinking over Night. The firſt thing he did was to examine his Pockets, which he found pretty weighty on one ſide, and on the other all his old Gold intire in the Purſe. His hands indeed were dirty, and he had all the other ſigns of a Bacchanalian, but an empty Pocket. He was gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally very pleaſant, and witty after a Debauch; for he was always ſure to drink the beſt Wines. Well! He lay till Eight reflecting on his Good and Evil Fortune, at length, after he had ſtretched and wiſhed for his <hi>Ariadne;</hi> falſe or true, ſhe would then have ſerv'd turn: After that (I ſay) he turns out and dreſſes. When he had done that, and his Devotions, he ſat him down, and writ as follows.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:153254:39"/>
                  <head>To <hi>Ariadne.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Madam,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Had the good Fortune yeſterday to be in a place where I preſume you dropt a Purſe of Gold and a Diamond-Ring, which I am come to reſtore, and only beg, you wou'd permit me the honour of kiſſing your hand: I fear, I am utterly a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to you, yet I beſeech you <hi>(Madam)</hi> Refuſe not this Obligation to</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Ladyſhips moſt Obedient, Humble Servant. <hi>Beaufort.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>When he had Written it, he knew not where to direct its And was in a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Perplexities about it, but in the end he took heart of Grace, and reſolv'd on
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:153254:39"/>
a Viſit to Sir <hi>Francis Heartwell,</hi> with whom, 'twas ten to one, but he found <hi>Marwoud.</hi> He took Coach then imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately, and came ſoon enough to his Brother in Law's Houſe to take him at home; and to his greater ſatifaction there was <hi>Marwoud</hi> too: Tho he did not in the leaſt contribute to his Information of the place of <hi>Ariadne</hi>'s Retreat, as it happen'd. For, after the firſt Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were over, Sir <hi>Francis</hi> ſate him down to make an end of a Letter, which he was then diſpatching to his Siſter, to enquire of his Couſin's Health, or if there were any need of his Preſence? Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoon as he had finiſh'd it, he deſir'd <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woud</hi> to fold it up, Seal it and Write the Superſcription? <hi>For</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>I have not ſeen</hi> Polydor <hi>ſo long, that I am un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to loſe one Minute of his Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation. You! muſt direct it</hi> (continu'd he) <hi>To my Sister, at my Lady</hi> Courtin's, <hi>two Miles wide of St.</hi> Alban<hi>'s. Polydor,</hi> overjoy d at ſuch a Bleſſed Opportunity of ſeeing the true <hi>Ariadne</hi> with a Letter from her Brother. Immediately offer'd his Service to preſent it to her; Adding,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:153254:40"/>
               <hi>It cou'd be no trouble to him, becauſe he had oblig'd himſelf to be at St.</hi> Albans <hi>by two a' Clock at fartheſt.</hi> Sir <hi>Francis</hi> told him, <hi>by no means he wou'd be guilty of ſuch a Rudeneſs;</hi> and that he had already <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded one of his Servants to deliver it, and to bring him an account of his Couſin's Health, the next day aſſoon as poſſible. Polydor</hi> urg'd on the other ſide, that he <hi>muſt of neceſſity return himſelf too, the next day, before Dinner, to meet Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny at</hi> Baniſters. <hi>However,</hi> Sir, (ſaid the over Courteous Knight) <hi>I can by no means permit it. Polydor</hi> was then juſt going to tell him that he had buſineſs with her, and diſcover the Ring and the Gold to them, and how he came by 'em; but that he conſider'd, if they ſhou'd not prove Sir <hi>Francis</hi>'s Siſters, they wou'd but Laugh at him for his Credulity; or, if they were really hers; ſhe on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide might be diſpleaſed at the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery</p>
            <p>But after all, he determin'd with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to ſet out with the Knight's Servant, and to his greater Comfort, he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the Footman was not to begin his
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:153254:40"/>
Journey till after Dinner: For he was to carry ſome things with him from the Change, which cou'd not be ready till about one. <hi>Polydor</hi> therefore had time enough to provide him of a good Horſe; which he did aſſoon as he parted from Sir <hi>Francis</hi> and <hi>Marwoud.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After he was fix'd with every thing for his Journey, he betook him to a little Alehouſe almoſt over againſt the Knights Houſe, whence aſſoon as he ſaw the Footman come; he mounted and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd him at a convenient diſtance. 'Tis true, he let him ride a good way before him till they got clear off the Stones; but about a Mile out o' Town, he over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took him. <hi>O Friend</hi> (ſaid <hi>Polydor) well overtaken! Your Servant</hi> (ſaid the Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man) <hi>I'm very glad that</hi> I <hi>ſhall have the honour to wait on you moſt part of your Journey.</hi> I <hi>thank thee</hi> (reply'd <hi>Polydor.) — But—What!</hi> (continu'd he) <hi>Is it your young Lady, Madam</hi>—A— Ariadne <hi>that is ſick? No Sir,</hi> (anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Servant) <hi>'Tis a Couſin of hers. Nay</hi> (ſaid <hi>Polydor) I only ask'd that Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, becauſe Mr.</hi> Marwoud <hi>gave me
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:153254:41"/>
this Letter juſt as</hi> I <hi>left your Maſter and him, and I think he talk'd of ſomthing there was of advice in it:</hi> Saying ſo, he gave him his own Letter to <hi>Ariadne. Is this for my Lady Sir</hi> (ſaid the Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.) <hi>Yes,</hi> (anſwer'd <hi>Polydor) for your Maſters Siſter. I'le take care to deliver it, Sir</hi> (ſaid the Footman.) <hi>Prithe do!</hi> (reply'd <hi>Polydor) There is an anſwer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, and pray let me have it; for,</hi> I <hi>have engag'd my ſelf to bring him what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhe is pleas'd to ſend him.</hi> I <hi>Prophecy</hi> (ſaid the Servant) <hi>What her anſwer will be: For</hi> I <hi>am ſure this is a Love-Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Nay, may be ſo</hi> (cry'd <hi>Polydor.) However</hi> (continu'd the Footman) <hi>I'le de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver it very faithfully to her, for I have a great reſpect for my honeſt Maſter</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woud. <hi>I'me ſure.</hi> (added he) <hi>I have had many a Half-Crown of him, nay, many a Crown, I may ſay; ſince</hi> I <hi>have known him. O</hi> (cry'd <hi>Polydor) if thou had'ſt not ſpoke on't, I fear, my Memory is ſo Treacherous, I ſhou'd ha' done thee wrong. Here</hi> (continu'd he pulling Money out of his Pocket) <hi>Here's a Guinny for thee which he ſent thee. I thank you Sir,</hi>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:153254:41"/>
(ſaid the Footman receiving it) <hi>But he is always too bountiful; I wou'd ha' ſerv'd him ten times more without a quarter of this. No doubt of that</hi> (ſaid <hi>Polydor) But prithee</hi> (continu'd he) <hi>what anſwer doſt thou think ſhee'l ſend him? Alas Sir</hi> (replyed the Footman) <hi>a very cold or ſcornful one, I fear. Then ſhe does not Love him?</hi> (ſaid <hi>Polydor) O, no Sir: I believe</hi> (ſaid the Footman) <hi>ſhe wou'd not endure to ſee him, were it not in Complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance to Sir</hi> Francis. <hi>How ſo!</hi> (cry'd <hi>Polydor) he is a handſom Man. Ah, Sir!</hi> (anſwer'd the Footman) <hi>As long as ſhe does not think him ſo; what advantage is his handſomneſs to him; in that caſe! Th'art in the right</hi> (ſaid <hi>Polydor) But —How long has he lov'd her? Above theſe</hi> 2 <hi>Years</hi> (reply'd the Servant) They had a great deal more diſcourſe concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Ariadne</hi>'s Scorn, and <hi>Marwoud</hi>'s Love, which Entertain'd 'em till they came within two Miles of the Houſe where the Footman was to go. <hi>Now</hi> (Friend, (ſaid <hi>Polydor) ſince, as thou ſai'ſt, we are ſo near the Lady's houſe; ſhew we ſome little blind Ale-houſe or hedge
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:153254:42"/>
Tavern as nigh it as may be: That I may expect an anſwer of</hi> Marwoud<hi>'s Letter, by thee aſſoon as poſſible. I will Sir,</hi> (ſaid the Footman.)</p>
            <p>So they Rode on a Mile farther, and the Footman Lodg'd him at a little thatched Houſe, where they ſold good Nappy Ale. There <hi>Polydor</hi> treated himſelf and his Horſe, which drank Ale as freely as his Rider did Clarret. <hi>Polydor</hi> was Curſing <hi>Marwoud</hi> heartily, though as yet he was not certain whether it was his <hi>Ariadne</hi> or no. In the mean time the Footman came to his Poſt, and delivered his Letters.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ariadne</hi> not knowing <hi>Polydor</hi>'s hand, and being very curious to ſee what was in his Letter, opened it firſt: and look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then on the Name, ſhe was much more ſurpriſed by reading it; ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to gueſs who 'twas. <hi>What manner of Gentleman</hi> (ſaid ſhe to the Footman) <hi>was he who gave you this? A very fine handſome Gentleman Madam,</hi> (reply'd the Footman) <hi>ſomething with the talleſt, delicately ſhaped, yet very ſtrongly ſet, of a dark brown Complexion, and hazle
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:153254:42"/>
Eyes, with a few marks of the ſmall Pox in his Face.</hi> By this Deſcription ſhe knew it muſt be <hi>Polydor. Well</hi> (ſaid ſhe ſmiling, which ſhe could not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear) <hi>don't ſet up your Horſe yet, you muſt go fetch the Gentleman hither.</hi> With that ſhe goes immediately to the young Lady her Couſin, to whom ſhe had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready related her adventure with <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lydor,</hi> and deſires her Aſſiſtance in tormenting him a little. (Said ſhe) <hi>I muſt get you to Perſonate me. Here is the Letter he ſent me. But you muſt tell him, you know nothing of a Ring or of Gold:</hi> theſe and a few more Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons made the young Lady <hi>Dorothea,</hi> (for ſo ſhe was call'd) very perfect in her part. <hi>Miranda</hi> and <hi>Ariadne</hi> were to keep out of ſight.</p>
            <p>When they had agreed upon all cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances to deceive him, <hi>Ariadne</hi> ſent the Footman to tell <hi>Polydor,</hi> that his Lady <hi>Ariadne,</hi> deſired to ſee him, and charged him, not to deſcribe her Perſon to him, but to bring him di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly to <hi>Dorothea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The honeſt Fellow obliged her very
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:153254:43"/>
exactly, and brought <hi>Polydor</hi> to <hi>Doro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thea,</hi> who by this time really thought her ſelf to be <hi>Ariadne. Polydor</hi> at the ſight of her, was ſo confounded and grieved to find it was not his <hi>Ariadne,</hi> that he was ready to ſink down. <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rothea</hi> ſeeing him in that ruful Poſture began firſt, <hi>Sir</hi> (ſaid ſhe) <hi>I ſuppoſe this is your Letter to me. It is</hi> (Madam) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd <hi>Polydor,</hi> fetching a deep ſigh) <hi>but I find my Errour, you are not the Lady Madam. Indeed I am not Sir,</hi> (anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Dorothea.) No! (Madam</hi> Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted <hi>Polydor,</hi> with a pittious Groan) <hi>To my Eternal ſhame, Sorrow and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, you are not my</hi> Ariadne. <hi>Pardon me, I beſeech you Madam! and to ſhew you that this is not meerly a Pretence; ſee here the Ring, and the Purſe of Gold, which I wrote of to your Ladyſhip. I once more beg you would forgive this Rudeneſs, and forget</hi> Beaufort. <hi>I am your moſt Obedient Servant Madam,</hi> Continued he bowing and went out.</p>
            <p>The Compaſſionate pretty Lady was ſo concerned for him, that ſhe was once or twice going to call him back
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:153254:43"/>
to diſcover the fallacy to Him: But knowing <hi>Ariadnes</hi> humour ſhe durſt not: for fear of diſobliging her. However ſhe went to her, with reſolution to chide her ſeverely, for ſo ill treating ſo <hi>hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome a Gentleman</hi> (as ſhe call'd him) <hi>and one who She durſt engage loved her moſt paſſionately. So much the better</hi> (ſaid A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riadne) <hi>I am glad to hear it. But ere it be too late</hi> (continued ſhe) <hi>I muſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch this Fellow that came with him to obſerve where he takes up his Quarters, for you have not performed half your part with him yet. O Heavens!</hi> (cry'd <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rothea</hi> almoſt ready to weep) <hi>I am re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved I'le not torture the poor wretch any more. Let Miranda do't an She will! — So I promiſe you, She ſhould</hi> (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd Ariadne) <hi>if it were convenient, but She knows her too well. And in ſhort</hi> (continued ſhe) <hi>you are the fittest Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon alive. My Dear</hi> (purſu'd ſhe, ſweetning the tone of her Voice, and kiſſing her Cheek) <hi>you muſt oblige me. Nay</hi> (ſaid Dorothea) <hi>ſince my</hi> Ariadne <hi>ſays there is a Neceſſity for it, I ſhall obey. Well</hi> (ſaid Ariadne) <hi>I thank thee
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:153254:44"/>
my Dear, I'le inſtruct thee preſently, aſſoon as I have ſent this Footman after him.</hi> VVhich ſhe did immediately, and returned to her fair Scholar, and her Dear <hi>Miranda.</hi> Now (ſaid ſhe to the firſt) <hi>You muſt know I will write a moſt paſſionate Love-Letter to him, as if I had fall'n in Love with him at firſt ſight, and invite him hither, where you are to ſecond what I ſhall write, and pretend you are deeply in Love with him. O fy!</hi> (interrupted Dorothea) <hi>I profeſs you impoſe a very difficult task on me; and to ſay truth, I am the rather more avers to this, leſt in pretending it, I ſhould really Love him — O! No,</hi> (reply'd Ariadne) <hi>think on me, and you are ſecure enough. Yet I vow to you</hi> (interrupted Miranda) <hi>'tis very hard to Counterfeit love to a Man of his Addreſs and Perſon. Very fine</hi> (cry'd Ariadne) <hi>I ſee I have two dangerous Rivals of you. Yet this must be done. Be ſatisfied!</hi> (ſaid Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rothea) <hi>It ſhall, It ſhall.</hi> Thus as they had been diſcourſing, and plotting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt poor wretched <hi>Polydor,</hi> for about an hours ſpace; The Footman returned
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:153254:44"/>
and gave them an Accountorious as my betaken himſelf to the litt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es of the Houſe where he left him at <hi>Ay</hi> (purſu'd how long he would continue there, he could not poſitively ſay.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ariadne</hi> upon this wrote a Letter immediately, as ſhe had before deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and obliged the Compaſſionate <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rothea</hi> to Act out her part, while <hi>Poloydor</hi> lay Raving on a Flock-B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d in the little Ale-Houſe, not at all regarding or fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Vermin that might aſſault him. Now if I had been he, I would rather have ſat down and drank with my Horſe, than have ventured my Boots in ſo ſuſpicious a Place. For all my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light is in clean Linnen, (as the VVench ſaid when ſhe waſhed her diſh-Clout.) But he not at all Curious, Sollicitous; Anxious or uneaſy for his Apartment; began a large and bitter Satyr againſt VVomen; and concluded with no great Encomium of his own Diſcretion. <hi>Ah</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>was ever man ſo Credulous! ſo eaſily deluded; by a little Lewd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ilting Scrumpet! O Beaſt! and which is worſt, O, Cuckold!</hi> (continued he, ſcratching
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:153254:45"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:153254:45"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:153254:46"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re it did not itch.) Now had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enchify'd, and had it been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, or Fall of the Leaf, it were not Ridiculous to ſuppoſe he might have Entertained his fingers ends with a budding Maid or two; But I dare aſſure you, he was as ſound as a Roach, and beſides it was Summer. Yet tho he was thus tender of his Honour, he could not but admire and commend to himſelf his <hi>Ariadnes</hi> Beauty and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour. <hi>O!</hi> (cry'd he aloud) <hi>were not this Creature falſe,</hi> (for did you mark? that's generally the firſt word your Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous or forſaken Lovers call one another) <q>had ſhe not been falſe, <hi>(repeated he)</hi> ſhe were worth a Thouſand ſuch <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adnes</hi> as I ſaw laſt, yet I muſt own by the little notice I took of her, ſhe was extreamly Beautiful too! — But <hi>(con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued he all in a rage)</hi> my Devil is ſo Charming, that if ſhe were already re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally a Devil, <hi>(as in time no doubt She may)</hi> ſhe would invite a Saint to her Embraces. Well! I am a Cuckold! and Ile go herd in the City, my Horns will not be perceived there: at leaſt
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:153254:46"/>
they may not be ſo notorious as my Elder Brothers the Deputies of the Ward where I fix. <hi>Ay, Ay</hi> (purſu'd he) and I'le throw off my Sword, and turn as great a Cheat as any Tradeſman of them all! As great a Rebel, and as great an Hypocrite as any Puritan Villain among them, nay more (ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded he fiercely) I cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d almoſt find in my heart to write-Pamphlets a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>D.</hi> and call the Kings late moſt Gracious De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>laration a Libel. But hold, <hi>ſaid he coming a little to himſelf,</hi> It muſt not go there. No, let her be damn'd by her ſelf, I will not perſwade my ſelf to theſe Imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties leſt I keep her Company. Ah, Polydor! <hi>continued he;</hi> what will thy Mother, thy Brother, thy Siſters, and all thy Relations ſay to this, will they not ſcorn thee? will they not point at thee, and ſhun thee? For there is nothing in the World ſo contemptible to each other, as Relations, when any one of them Miſcarries. Nay, and it carries with it ſome ſhew of Reaſon. 'Tis a diſgrace to the whole Family! What
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:153254:47"/>
                  <hi>ſays one,</hi> Marry a VVhore! A Jilt! O Devil! — Why I ſhall become a Town-talk! Be ſung about the Streets in a Ballad to the tune of <hi>Fortune my Foe.</hi> Married! <hi>ſays another,</hi> with a Plague, what need he have Married! He always ſeemed averſe to it. —But I beg your pardon Sir, <hi>purſu'd he,</hi> If this Woman had been really what ſhe pretended, I would not have been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>married for an Empire. — But ſhees Falſe! and I am Loſt, Ruin'd, and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally miſerable.</q>
            </p>
            <p>If all this ſhou'd be true now that he ſays, there is no body but would pitty him. But Well! He ſaid no more for the preſent: only he hurried up and down about the Room moſt Violently; as I have ſeen a Mouſe looking for a hole to eſcape at. In this motion <hi>Ariadnes</hi> Meſſenger found him, and delivered his Lady's Letter to him, which held theſe words.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:153254:47"/>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>Though you miſtook, when you thought you had found a Ring and Gold that belonged to me; yet I am not miſtaken in accuſing you, as the Man that has ſtoll'n my Heart and Rob'd me of my Quiet: which unleſs you immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſtore with your Preſence, I am re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to haunt you, as long as I am</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Ariadne.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>Hey day,</hi> (cry'd Polydor with a ſcornful Smile) <q>What's here! more ſport for Fortune! Her Ladyſhip (me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks) is merrily diſpoſed at preſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Pray honeſt Friend and fellow Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellor <hi>(ſaid he to the Footman)</hi> what does your Lady mean by this? Alas <hi>(Sir reply'd the Footman)</hi> I thought that Paper had fully diſcover'd her In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions to you: I am only to entreat you would pleaſe to let me wait on you to her Immediately. Humh! Immediately! <hi>(cry'd Polydor to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf)</hi>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:153254:48"/>
Her Ladyſhip's mighty warm on the ſuddain! But I' gad, ſhee's miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken her Man, as it happens. The curſe on't is, nothing will go down with me now, but that ſame other falſe <hi>Ariad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne.</hi> How ever I ſhall oblige her ſo far for her Brothers ſake, for Civility's ſake, and for our Families ſake, who never refuſ'd a Viſit to a pretty Lady. There may (perhaps) too, be more Gold, or more Rings coming: but I fear, I ſhan't deſerve 'em. Poor La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy! I'm ſorry for her. I am an Elder Brother in my humour, and cannot drudge for a Livelyhood. Well! Come Friend (continued he turning to the Footman) <hi>I'le go with you,</hi> ſo on they walk'd to the Lady, where I'le leave 'em a while.</q>
            </p>
            <p>His Guide ſoon Conducted him to the Couterfeit <hi>Ariadne,</hi> who expected him in her Cloſet, aſſoon as ſhe ſaw him, ſhe was in ſuch diſorder, and her thoughts were ſo confus'd, that ſhe cou'd not ſay one word to him. She bluſh'd and caſt down her Eyes, as if ſhe had really been Guilty of loving him. <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lydor</hi>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:153254:48"/>
took notice of it; And began, ſhewing her the Billet ſhe ſent him. <q>If this Paper (Madam) has diſcover'd more than you will own, be pleaſed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn it to the Flames, and Sacrifice it to your Indignation. I muſt confeſs <hi>(continu'd he)</hi> 'tis that has occaſion'd you the trouble of a ſecond Viſit</q> — By this time ſhe had pretty well reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd her ſelf, and anſwer'd him. <q>'Tis true Sir, that Paper has caus'd the Confuſion, which (perhaps) you might obſerve I was in at the ſight of you. But if it had not done me the good Office of diſcovering my deareſt thoughts to you; believe me, I ſhou'd have had no little difficulty to perſwade my ſelf to it. And (continu'd ſhe) I muſt needs Juſtify what you have read there. But I muſt Chide you, (pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu'd ſhe with an obliging Smile) I muſt Chide you <hi>Beaufort</hi> for calling that a Trouble, which is the greateſt Obligation you could have done me at preſent.</q> Pray ſit (ſaid ſhe taking him by the hand) they both ſat down, <hi>Polydor</hi> fixing his Eyes on hers, as if
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:153254:49"/>
he ſeem'd to ask them what ſhe would be at? <q>You expect (perhaps ſaid <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rothea</hi>) that I ſhould make an Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy for my Modeſty, which probably you may think I have violated, in treating thus familiarly with a Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. But I ſhall only ſay, you are very unkind if you do, ſince you were the cauſe of it your ſelf. And give me leave to add, 'twas Love, 'twas Almighty Love that forc'd me to this Extravagance. Beſides (purſu'd ſhe) I did not know how ſoon you would leave us and the Country: nor could I tell where to have enquired of you. Madam <hi>(reply'd Polydor)</hi> I confeſs, it had not been very eaſy to have met with me by that name. And I beſeech you pardon me <hi>(continued he)</hi> and I will undeceive you. <hi>He paus'd, but ſeeing ſhe expected he ſhould proceed.</hi> My name <hi>(purſu'd he)</hi> is Polydor; I am not altogether unknown to your Brother Sir <hi>Francis.</hi> Why then <hi>(in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted Dorothea)</hi> did you borrow an other name. Becauſe Madam <hi>(re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd he)</hi> I would have been wholly
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:153254:49"/>
diſguis'd to you, for ſome Reaſons that are not fit to be diſcours'd. And I beg you (Madam <hi>added he</hi>) not to preſs me to the diſcovery of them. Alas! I do not mean it Sir, (reply'd the fair Impoſtor) I have other Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with you, and of greater Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to my ſelf. I have Propoſals to make to you which (happily) may not prove abſolutely Diſadvantageous to you, if embrac'd.</q> I love you (<hi>Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor</hi> continued ſhe, without ſuffering him to ſpeak.) <q>And I love you ſo paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionately, that I can be capable of no reſt, nor ſenſible of any Joy; unleſs you juſtly anſwer me.</q> Nay Madam (Interrupted <hi>Polydor</hi>) <q>As for that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter I can Love as faſt, and as well as any man. And I am ready to do your Ladyſhip any Civil Kindneſs.</q> Ah (cry'd ſhe) <q>I fear you miſtake me, <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lydor!</hi> my deſires and deſigns are ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and Honourable. — We muſt Marry (continued <hi>Dorothea</hi>) if you mean to make me Happy; If you will not kill a poor Lady that languiſhes for you. How! Marry! — (Interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:153254:50"/>
he) you don't know what you ask Madam. I wiſh I could with all my heart! But I have ſeen enough of that already. I hope in Heaven <hi>(cry'd Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rothea all in a ſurprize)</hi> you are not Married. Are you? If I be not; <hi>(an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered Polydor)</hi> I have ſeen the fatal Conſequences of it in others: No, no Madam <hi>(continued he)</hi> no more of that! ſuch another word and I ſhall Swown, though I nere uſe to do ſo. Why <hi>(re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd Dorothea)</hi> am I ſo contemptible then? if you are any way acquainted with my Brother, you may (perhaps) have heard my Fortunes are not. And <hi>(purſu'd ſhe)</hi> could it enter into your thoughts, that the Siſter of Sir <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Heartwell</hi> could ask any thing but Marriage of you, after the Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of her Love? Ah (Madam <hi>ſaid Polydor Kneeling</hi>) for Heavens ſake forgive me! I am certain you would (added he) if you knew my wretched, Curſed, Circumſtances. Heaven knows (purſu'd he, looking very A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mourouſly on her) I would ſoon em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace ſo advantageous an offer if it
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:153254:50"/>
were convenient for either of us. Seek not I beſeech you (continued he with a ſigh) ſeek not to know the miſerable Obſtacle. Be ſatisfied, I am loſt (Madam!) Condemned to perpetual Infamy while here I Live! My Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation is Damn'd, my Fortune and my Reſt for ever broken: And my Liberty is no more! Ah pitty Madam, (purſu'd he with a hearty ſigh) pitty a miſerable Creature, that is not cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able of receiving the Happineſs your Goodneſs would throw away upon him! And now (continu'd he riſing) Permit me I beg of you to retire, and Curſe my Evil Stars, which have heap'd ſo great Misfortunes on me, only for my Credulity; ſuffer me I Conjure you by your Excellent good Humour, to retire, that I may Rave freely alone! that I may either ſhake off the thoughts of my Miſery, or ſink under 'em. O Heavens! (cry'd <hi>Dorothea</hi> weeping, which by no means ſhe could refrain,) ſuch was the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of her Temper, I pitty you from my Soul. Alas! I cannot but
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:153254:51"/>
be too ſenſible that you are much Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted. And I wiſh heartily it were in my Power or Art to relieve you. You may go (continued he) ſince you muſt, and will go. But I beſeech you, as ever you hope to regain your Quiet, Let me at all times know where to find you.</q> Be confident Madam, you ſhall (ſaid <hi>Polydor</hi> kiſſing her Hand) and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his Obeyſance very humbly to the very Door, he left her gazing after him.</p>
            <p>When he was quite out of ſight, ſhe went to her cruel Couſin whom ſhe rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly'd ſeverely for making her Inſtrument in Torturing the Poor miſtaken <hi>Polydor.</hi> —But to her greater diſſatisfaction, ſhe underſtood, that ſhe had a Scene or two more to play of her part yet: Which <hi>Ariadne</hi> began to inſtruct her in. While <hi>Polydor</hi> retreated to his little Thatch'd houſe; where he weigh'd every Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of this Laſt Adventure.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Heavens! <hi>(cry'd he)</hi> was there ever ſo unfortunate a Fellow as I am, to be abus'd by a Counterfeit <hi>Ariadne,</hi> when I might really have had the true one! But, perhaps, I had never ſeen the laſt
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:153254:51"/>
had it not been in queſt of the firſt. 'Tis ſtranged Methinks, there is ſtill ſomething that hangs about my Heart and will not let me hate that naughty Woman, nor I fear I ſhou'd receive her again, were I aſſur'd of her Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue: Were I confident ſhe were not in Debt, or had I but an Eſtate to pay her Debts, whatever they were; up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the aſſurahce of her truth to me: I ſhou'd take her into my Boſom. O eaſy Fool that I am! I am certain I ſhou'd. Shee's witchingly fair! I cannot for my Soul forget her Beauty. Her Humour too ſo juſtly anſwers mine; that 'twere too great a Bleſſing for me to enjoy her had ſhe but Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour too. — But O! <hi>(continu'd he)</hi> I have loſt a Diamond for a Pebble. Is that ſo ſtrange! Alas! I have loſt my ſelf.— But well <hi>(purſued he)</hi> Ile to Town, and ſtrive to divert the Thoughts of my ill Fortune and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace with Company and Play. I may meet there with ſomebody as wretched as my ſelf: And then wee'l ſit and Rail, and Curſe Fortune, Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:153254:52"/>
and our own Follies — Hold, <hi>Polydor!</hi> Hold! <hi>(purſu'd he after a little Pauſe)</hi> Do's this become the greatneſs of thy Spirit! No; I will ſuffer quietly and ſilently. I'le be as great a Stoick as the beſt of 'em. Nay more; I'le bear my Afflictions like a Chriſtian Woman, I forgive thee. Thou haſt not Damned me yet. Thou haſt only made me forfeit all my Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs on Earth, unleſs I find it here, here in my Breaſt. I firſt muſt drive thee out and then I may. Alas! Thou coudſt not help this Treachery! It is Entail'd upon thy Sex. Heaven has ordain'd that you ſhou'd all be falſe. Made Soft and Fair the eaſier to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive.</q>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>'Twas not the Fruit nor Serpent ruin'd Man:</l>
               <l>O no! The Woman look'd the Sin into him!</l>
               <l>Shee Smil'd and raiſed ſtrong Appetites within him:</l>
               <l>The Mighty Charm prevail'd! The glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Bait.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:153254:52"/>He ſpeedily devour'd; and in one mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</l>
               <l>Thus Poyſon'd all his Pure, Immacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late Soul!</l>
               <l>And left his Sons weak Preys to's ſubtle Daughters!</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>So</hi> (continu'd he Recollecting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf) <hi>I can Preach I ſee, upon occaſion. However, this is no place to Preach in; the Night comes on apace; I will to Town in ſpite of Darkneſs.</hi> With that, he call'd for his Horſe and a Pen, Ink, and Paper; which with much ado he got: But, I believe, his Hoſteſs was forc'd to tear a blank Leaf out of the <hi>Practice of Piety</hi> or ſome ſuch Book; or, for ought I know, it might as well be torn out of the Famous Hiſtory of <hi>Valentine</hi> and <hi>Orſon;</hi> which indeed, is the moſt likely of the two: For as I underſtand, it was a Quarter of a ſheet of Paper; on which he wrote a piece of his Mind to the Counterfeit <hi>Ariadne,</hi> giving her no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice where ſhe might direct her Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands to him at any time; which he
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:153254:53"/>
diſpatch'd to her by a Meſſenger he found there, who undertook to deliver it that Night for a Teſter. So, immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately he mounted and came for <hi>London;</hi> where he Arriv'd about eleven at Night: He ſet up his Beaſt very carefully, and ſtay'd till he had ſeen his Bed made, and till he had eaten a hearty Supper of Corn. Then—<hi>God-a-mercy Horſe</hi> (ſaid <hi>Polydor</hi>) and left him to provide for his own ſelf; which he did; taking Coach and driving directly to his Lodgings; where he vow'd, Pray'd a little and Sigh'd more, ſo put out his Candle and went to Bed. What with Travelling and Vexation, he was ſo tir'd, that he ſlept very ſoundly till ſeven the next Morning, without the help of Wine. When he 'roſe he found himſelf much better for having drank ſo little the Day paſt: But ſtill he found his Troubles return into his Thoughts, as freſh as ever. He knew not what in the World to do, to eaſe himſelf. At laſt, he bethought himſelf of his Friend <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woud:</hi> To whom he reſolved to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe his Misfortunes at large and ask his Advice, what to do in his miſerable
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:153254:53"/>
Condition: For, he had fully determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in his Thoughts to drink no more ſo largely and frequently as he had done hitherto. To his miſtaken Friend then he go's, finds him hardly awake, in Bed. <hi>What! Not awake yet</hi> (ſaid <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lydor,</hi> drawing open the Curtains) <hi>Who's that?</hi> (cry'd <hi>Marwoud,</hi> rubbing his Eyes) <hi>O</hi> Polydor! <hi>What Return'd al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready! Will you believe your Eyes, or no,</hi> (reply'd <hi>Polydor) you ſee I am. Hardly</hi> (anſwer'd <hi>Marwoud) for faith thou haſt made ſuch haſt 'tis almoſt incredible to me! Since,</hi> I <hi>preſume, you stay'd ſome time with your Friends you went to ſee: And for my part,</hi> I <hi>declare to you, I don't love to ride ſo hard: But did you not travel ſome part of the laſt Night?</hi> (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinu'd he) I <hi>did,</hi> (reply'd <hi>Polydor</hi>) I <hi>ſhou'd not-like that without Company</hi> (ſaid <hi>Marwoud) 'tis dangerous, there are High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way-Men abroad every Night on that Road: Beſides if it were never ſo clear of them;</hi> I <hi>ſhou'd nevertheleſs be Aſſaulted by all the Melancholy Thoughts my Soul cou'd muſter. Ay!</hi> (interrupted <hi>Polydor) Thoſe were my Entertainment all the way.</hi>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:153254:54"/>
I <hi>never was ſo melancholy in all my Life,</hi> (added he) <hi>nor ever had reaſon to be ſo: How? Prithee why?</hi> (ſaid <hi>Marwoud) ſit on the Bed and let me hear the reaſon. You ſhall</hi> (ſaid <hi>Polydor</hi> ſitting down) I <hi>am Marry'd my dear Friend</hi> (continu'd he, embracing <hi>Marwoud;</hi> ſighing and almoſt weeping at every word) <hi>At laſt,</hi> he ſummon'd all his Reſolution, and made ſhift to diſcourſe all his Adventures with <hi>Ariadne</hi> to him, which he did in ſuch pitteous Accents and with ſuch mournful Geſtures, that <hi>Marwoud</hi> often ſigh'd in Conſort with him. But, perhaps, it was more, becauſe he underſtood that <hi>Polydor</hi> had rob'd him of his Miſtreſs, tho he did not know it himſelf. But as if it had been to make him more enra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged; <hi>Polydor</hi> ſhews him the Ring and Gold <hi>Ariadne</hi> left with him. <hi>Marwoud</hi> ſoon knew the Purſe and the Ring. Which made him ſay, coldly, <q>On my Word, I ſhou'd think by this ſhe were a Perſon of Quality; but her leaving you ſo ſtrangely confirms me in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Opinion,</q> 
               <hi>Polydor</hi> then proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to tell him how paſſionately in Love
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:153254:54"/>
the true <hi>Ariadne</hi> was with him, all along miſtaking <hi>Dorothea</hi> for her. <q>But (<hi>ſaid he tenderly embracing</hi> Marwoud <hi>again</hi>) I will have nothing to ſay to her, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, I know your Heart is engag'd there. How came you to hear that (<hi>ſaid</hi> Marwoud?) The Foot-man that I overtook on the Road diſcover'd it to me, by a trick I put upon him. Well then, <hi>cry'd</hi> Marwoud, how do you like the true <hi>Ariadne?</hi> What manner of Woman is ſhe? for, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, <hi>continu'd he,</hi> you may be ſtill deceiv'd. That's impoſſible, <hi>replyed</hi> Polydor, and to convince you that I am not, I will deſcribe her to you. Her Hair is of a pale brown, her Eyes are Gray, full and Languiſhing. She Liſps a little; and ſhe has a Mole on her left Cheek which become her ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly. Nay, nay, I'm ſure 'tis ſhe.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Well I am ſatisfy'd; <hi>ſaid</hi> Marwoud, who knew well enough 'twas <hi>Dorothea,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y the Deſcription:</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:153254:55"/>He preſently imagin'd 'twas one of <hi>Ariadnes</hi> Caprices that ſet <hi>Dorothea</hi> to perſonate her. He began to be very uneaſy, and impatient of <hi>Polydor</hi>'s Stay. — When <hi>Polydor</hi> asked him, <q>Am not I the moſt wretched Creature breathing? Doſt thou not pitty me heartily? What ſhall I do? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rithee aſſiſt me.</q> And a thouſand other things that a man in his Condition might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. He reply'd, <q>I believe 'tis Nine a Clock; I muſt riſe to take Sir Francis ere he go out. What? ſhall I drink a Bottle with you at Night? I will not fail to meet you at Eight, at Lockets, or where you will. I'le ſee you ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> if you pleaſe (reply'd Polydor) bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> I can't Drink. You dull Dog (ſaid Marwood to his <hi>Valet de Chambre</hi>) ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> theſe Clothes for this Weather? Wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> occaſion have I to Sweat this Weather more than I muſt of Neceſſity? Do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> your Rogueſhip think I'm Pox'd! yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are but an ill Phyſitian to preſcri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> me a Sweat, amid'ſt all this Heat, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> I were.</q> The poor Devil anſwer'd nere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> word, but with all ſubmiſſion imag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nable
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:153254:55"/>
brought him another Suit that look'd a little Cooler. He put it on and dreſſed, till he had occaſion for his Perruke; by ill Luck, that which he deſigned to wear that day, was not Comb'd out. — Defend us! How many <hi>Dammees?</hi> How many <hi>Oaths?</hi> How many <hi>Inſipi'd Raſcally Negligent Beaſts</hi> were there utter'd! <hi>Polydor</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving him out of Humour, did not know what certainly to attribute it to, but thought it very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onvenient to leave him. <hi>Marwood</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>good Morrow! To Night at Eight, at Lockets; remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber your Servant,</hi> anſwered he in the ſame Tone, he had ſpoken to his <hi>Valet de Chambre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Down Stairs went <hi>Polydor,</hi> and not long after <hi>Marwood</hi> took a Chair and went to Sir <hi>Francis,</hi> where he appear'd very much diſcompos'd, all along; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Sir <hi>Francis</hi> took part<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cular Notice of him. <q>Marwood (ſaid he) What the Devil ails thee? Thy looks are enough to give the moſt Coſtive Body a ſtool! What's the matter? Come, impart, impart 'Tis not whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:153254:56"/>
for your knowledge of all Mens, (reply'd Marwood) 'twill bliſter your Ears if I relate it. You ſeem to imply (ſaid the Knight) that it Concerns me. And your words have rais'd my Curioſity to that height, that you muſt explain 'em, or I cannot eſteem you my Friend. My ſilence (anſwer'd Marwood) is now the greateſt Argument of my Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to you that I can make you. I beg you would not. — Prithee do not beg (interrupted Sir Francis) thou haſt ſtirr'd all that was Woman in me, and now I muſt know; thy very Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to conceal it makes me im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient of this tormenting Silence. There's Miſchief in it, let me know it. Miſchief! I think there is (cry'd <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood all in a Rage</hi>) Miſchief, Baſe, Treacherous Miſcheif! Why then art thou ſo long ere thou let'ſt me know it? (ſaid <hi>Ariadnes</hi> dear Brothe.r) Too ſoon (ſaid <hi>Marwood,</hi> ſhaking his ſpite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful head, and ſhrugging up his Shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, you will know too ſoon, the Lady your Siſter <hi>Ariadne</hi> is Married. —
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:153254:56"/>
Married! (ſaid Sir <hi>Francis,</hi> keeping his Temper and his face.) Why, then God give her Joy! Can you then ſo Tamely hear ſuch ill News? (cry'd <hi>Marwood</hi>) that your Siſter is Marri'd baſely, below her ſelf to a Man of no Fortunes, or at leaſt of very ſmall For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, and thoſe too decaying! And without your Knowledge! With all my heart, let her Marry without my Knowledge (reply'd Sir <hi>Francis</hi>) But what baſe Man is he, ſhe has made her Husband? Pray what is his name? Do I know him? yes, I think you have ſeen him (anſwered <hi>Marwood</hi>) and in my Company. Pox o' my Log<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerhead that ever I brought him near you! — Prithee (interrupted the good humour'd Gentleman) who is he without any more Harrangues, let me know his Name, if he has one, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you. 'Tis <hi>Polydor,</hi> that Treach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erous Beggerly Villain! (cry'd <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood,</hi> his Face all over glowing with Rage and Envy.) <hi>Polydor!</hi> (ſaid Sir <hi>Francis</hi>) have a care <hi>Marwood</hi> what you ſay! He is a worthy Gentleman
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:153254:57"/>
and of a good Family, beſides he was your Friend. I am heartily glad 'tis ſo well with her, after all the fears you put me in for her. So well (cry'd <hi>Marwoud.</hi> 'Tis true; ſhe might have Married a Hangman, a Cobler, or a Porter for all you I ſee; But I don't apprehend how otherwiſe ſhe could have done worſe! The Extravagant Prodigal knows how to ſpend her Fortunes, and his own too, were they both doubled. Is this all the care you take of your Siſter! How now <hi>Marwoud!</hi> (ſaid Sir <hi>Francis</hi> putting on a ſerious Look) what do you mean by this Diſcourſe. Pray keep your Reprimands till they may be more ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable: will you inſtruct my Care and Love to my Siſter! If I have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended Sir, (anſwered <hi>Marwoud</hi>) 'tis through the exceſs of my Friendſhip, and Zeal to ſerve you. I could not think ſuch a Loſt Fellow as <hi>Polydor,</hi> a fit Match, for the incomparable <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riadne.</hi>
               </q> It ſeems <hi>(reply'd her Brother) Ariade thinks ſo.</hi> 
               <q>And once more I give you Caution, that you treat him
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:153254:57"/>
at your diſcourſe of him, as he is a Gentleman. If not for his own, and his Families ſake, yet at leaſt as he is my Siſters Husband, and my Brother, — But how came this Wedding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout.</q> 
               <hi>Marwoud</hi> told him every Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance as <hi>Polydor</hi> had related to him, <q>but <hi>(added he)</hi> I fear he has diſguiſed the Truth, and that he ſurpriſed her, and forc'd her conſent to Marry him. If ſo <hi>(replyd Sir Francis)</hi> I ſhall take an Honourable Revenge on him: Wee'l go down to Morrow, and learn the Truth. But I fear, <hi>Marwoud</hi> you love her, your ſelf: I have long ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected it, and 'tis Jealous hate that makes you judge ſo ill of your happy Rival. I hope (reply'd <hi>Marwoud</hi> ready to burſt with Anger, which he durſt not vent there) I had not been altogether ſo Contemptible and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proportionate a Match; had I been ſo happy as <hi>Polydor.</hi> I grant your Eſtate is proportionable (reply'd Sir <hi>Francis</hi>) but how unequal your Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours may be, I know not. And (perhaps added he ſharply) ſhe is as
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:153254:58"/>
Happy as ſhe has diſpoſed of her ſelf, as if ſhe had proceeded according to your deliberate Inſtructions.</q> 'Tis very poſſible (reply'd <hi>Marwoud.</hi>)</p>
            <p>The next Morning they came to <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rotheas,</hi> where I fancy they were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, becauſe they were ſo Civilly entertain'd. Aſſoon as Sir <hi>Francis</hi> found his Siſter in private, which you may, be confident was before <hi>Marwoud</hi> had the opportunity of converſing alone with her. He told her all that <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woud</hi> had related to him, all which ſhe own'd, who certainly gave her the greateſt animoſity imaginable againſt a Gentleman of his Principles, and Circumſtances. 'Tis true ſhe was Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veng'd and that by good Fortune, for (perhaps) <hi>Marwoud</hi> durſt have fought any man on equal terms of Honour or Advantage. He was a Spark that could Love as heartily for intereſt as any man Breathing! He had a ſtrange Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand over himſelf in Converſation! And would ſeldom ſpeak Truth, for, that is the rudeſt thing imaginable, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially if a man always does ſo. You
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:153254:58"/>
are to know then, that aſſoon as her Brother had made this Diſcourſe to her, <hi>Ariadne</hi> ſingled out <hi>Marwoud,</hi> and led him into the Garden. <hi>Is it poſſible</hi> (ſaid ſhe) <hi>that a Gentleman and your friend, ſhould impudently and falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly report to you, that I was Married to him! and is it not as ſtrange that you ſhould give Credit to him on ſo ſlight Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, as the ſight of my Ring and Purſe. Look here</hi> (continued ſhe, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him the Letter <hi>Polydor</hi> had written to her, under the borrowed Name of <hi>Beaufort.) See now are you not finely abuſed. But I perceive very faint ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances will prevail on you, to believe the worſt things imaginable of me. Ha!</hi> (interrupted <hi>Marwoud</hi> in a pleaſing ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe) <hi>Are you not then Married to him? Why can't you yet give Credit to me!</hi> (ſaid Ariadne.) <hi>Why then</hi> (cry'd Marwoud) <hi>do you ſuffer him to wear thoſe things, which are much more precious in their having been worn by you, than an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred times their Value could make them? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou ſee</hi> (anſwered ſhe) <hi>he entreates here <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat he might kiſs my hand; which by
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:153254:59"/>
no means I would permit, but prevailed with Dorothea to perſonate me,</hi> when upon the firſt ſight of her, he cry'd ſhe was not that <hi>Ariadne</hi> he looked for, and left her without returning any of 'em. <hi>By Heaven but he ſhall return 'em Madam,</hi> (cry'd Marwood in a fierce tone) <hi>and that ere to Morrow this time. I would not</hi> (ſaid Ariadne) <hi>Encourage you in any ill deſign of Revenge upon my Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count; but truly I muſt ſay, he deſerves to be puniſhed for his Indiſcretion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What a Devil did this Woman mean now, (ſome will ſay) to ſet this Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low to Murther her Husband, Let them know ſhe was reſolved to try his Courage as well as his other Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues; for undoubtedly ſhe was the moſt humorous Creature Breathing. And I dare ſay, ſhe wiſh'd from her very Soul, that <hi>Polydor</hi> might come off Vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious, and Chaſtize <hi>Marwoud</hi> for his Tatling.</p>
            <p>They ſaid not much more on that Matter, becauſe they ſaw Sir <hi>Francis</hi> leading <hi>Dorothea</hi> and <hi>Miranda</hi> to them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> they joyned Diſcourſe preſently, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:153254:59"/>
News, and things indifferent, which laſted about an Hour: when they were told that Dinner waited them on the Table, they all went in, and thoſe could fed heartily; <hi>Marwoud's</hi> Stomack was full already, with his Reſolution of figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Polydor,</hi> and I think he Eate but little, but drank the more. And aſſoon as Dinner was over, he took the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to leave the Knight and Ladys in a very hot Diſpute, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Conſtancy of Men, and the Inconſtancy of Women, in affairs of Love.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Marwoud</hi> had gotten on Horſe-back juſt as they were beginning to be warm in their Arguments, and ordered one of the Footmen to tell Sir <hi>Francis,</hi> if he ſhould ask for him, that he was gone to make a Viſit to a Drunken friend of his about 7 or 8 Miles thence; and that he ſhould not wonder if he did not return to Night, for he doubted there might be hot Service.</p>
            <p>Having left this Charge with the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, he Rode for <hi>London,</hi> with all the Convenient ſpeed that might be; where
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:153254:60"/>
he found himſelf about Nine a Clock. He was ſo Impatient, that he hardly could give himſelf time to change his Boots for Shoos, ere he went to ſee for <hi>Polydor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By good fortune for him, he could not light on him that Night: But the next Morning early he took him in Bed. <hi>Polydor</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>you muſt riſe I have Buſineſs with you.</hi> This he ſpoke in a Tone ſo different, from that he uſed to ſalute his Friend in formerly, that <hi>Polydor</hi> almoſt gueſſed what he intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which made him ſay Riſing, <q>Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly your Buſineſs with me is very ſtrange and urgent, that you Viſit me thus early, and with that unuſual Roughneſs which you are not wont to accoſt me with. But (continued he) I am ready to give my Friends all manner of ſatisfaction becoming a Gentleman. I know it <hi>Polydor</hi> (ſaid <hi>Marwoud</hi>) elſe I had not given my ſelf the trouble to call you to an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, for an Injury done to a Perſon of Quality, and my moſt reſpected Acquaintance. I don't know what
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:153254:60"/>
you mean (anſwer'd <hi>Polydor</hi>) but I'le give you the beſt account <hi>I</hi> can. You muſt reſtore the Ring and Purſe which you pretended was given you by <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adne.</hi> How! <hi>Marwoud</hi> (ſaid <hi>Polydor</hi>) pretended to be given me! — And muſt Reſtore them. Prithee to whom? To me (reply'd <hi>Marwoud.</hi>) No <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woud</hi> (cry'd he) Not ſo. Bring me to that <hi>Ariadne</hi> that gave me the Ring, and left the Purſe with me; and you may prevent farther Miſchief. Talk not of preventing (ſaid <hi>Marwoud) I</hi> came to ſeek it. On my word, reply'd <hi>Polydor,</hi> you are fonder on't than I am.</q> 
               <hi>However I will help you to as much as may ſatisfie you, within this Hour; if you pleaſe to let me ſee you behind Claren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Houſe. Well! Good Morrow</hi> (ſaid Marwoud) <hi>I'le expect you there an hour hence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He went directly to the place ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, where <hi>Polydor</hi> after he was dreſſed, according to a laudable Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom which he had always obſerved; threw himſelf on his Knees, and recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended the Care of his Soul and Body
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:153254:61"/>
to Heaven: And I believe, if with Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour he might have avoided it, he wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d not have fought any man in cold Blood, much leſs one that had been his Friend. He could not yet imagine what obliged <hi>Marwoud</hi> to demand the Ring and Gold.</p>
            <p>He went conſidering on the odneſs of that Mornings Encounter, till he came to the aforeſaid place, where he found <hi>Marwoud</hi> ready to receive him, with all the Gallantry and Reſolution of a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous Enemy Said <hi>Polydor, I could wiſh Marwoud, that this matter might be otherwiſe determin'd, than by the Sword. Eſpecially between us two. 'Tis in vain</hi> (reply'd Marwoud drawing) <hi>The Sword alone muſt end this Diſpute with one of our Lives. Forbid it Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> (ſaid <hi>Polydor</hi> ſtanding on his Guard) <hi>Marwoud</hi> was very Furious and Violent in his Paſſes, which <hi>Polydor</hi> very calmly put by. But <hi>Marwoud</hi> continuing very eager, made one home Thruſt, and ſlightly wounded <hi>Polydor</hi> in his left Arm; who immediately threw him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into his enraged Enemy and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arm'd
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:153254:61"/>
him. <hi>Here Marwoud</hi> (ſaid <hi>Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor) take your Sword, I will not injure your Courage ſo mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> as to expect you ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>d ask your Life. What damn'd miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes this!</hi> (cry'd Marwoud receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Sword, <hi>I thank thee</hi> Polydor; <hi>but I muſt again employ it againſt thy Life! I muſt be ungrateful</hi> (continued he) <hi>my unhappy Circumſtances oblige me to it!—That's ſomewhat hard</hi> (reply'd Polydor) <hi>however I cannot fear to fight that man a ſecond time, whom I have once diſarm'd. And now Sir</hi> (added he with a threatning Geſture.) <hi>This bout may be more fatal to you than the former. I'le take it as it comes</hi> (ſaid Marwoud.)</p>
            <p>They both made ſeveral Paſſes, and <hi>Polydor</hi> was run quite through the right Thigh, but it was only a Fleſh-wound, having miſt the Sinews. This vex'd him heartily, and he preſt moſt V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly on his Rival, inſomuch that he made him retreat about two yards of Ground, and purſuing his Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage ran him into the Sword Arm, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt as far as his Breaſt. There his Sword was ſo engag'd, that he could
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:153254:62"/>
not eaſily get it out: mean while <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woud</hi> was ſhifting his own Sword into his left hand, that he might ſhorten it, and run him into the Back, but <hi>Polydor</hi> prevented him by throwing him on the Ground, where he took from him both the Swords. <hi>Marwoud's</hi> he ſtuck into the Earth, and broke it ſhort almoſt to the Hilt. <hi>Now</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>Marwoud thou haſt the Reward of Ingratitude farewell, if thou canſt; I'le ſend ſomebody to help thee, aſſoon as I reach the Town. No, hold!</hi> (ſaid Marwood) <hi>let me walk with you. I have my due, and I am ſatisfied. And I thank Heaven that we have both ſcap'd with Life. No thanks to you though Sir</hi> (ſaid Polydor.)</p>
            <p>They both made ſhift to get to St. <hi>Jamſes,</hi> where they took Coach, and were both Carried to the ſame Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeon, who aſſur'd 'em there was no great danger on either ſide; but <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woud's</hi> was ſomewhat the worſe. When the Wounds were dreſſed, they em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced very kindly, and were as good friends ſeemingly, as ever they had been formerly. I dare engage that <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lydor</hi>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:153254:62"/>
was real, but for <hi>Marwoud,</hi> I can not ſay much, for he plaid him an ill trick after this.</p>
            <p>They parted for the preſent and went to their ſeveral Lodgings. About twelve a Clock Sir <hi>Francis</hi> came in puffing haſt to <hi>Marwouds,</hi> whom he found upon his Bed aſleep, and in a fine breathing Sweat. He was going to ſteal away ſoftly to leave him to his Repoſe, but (it ſeems) he could not avoid making ſo much Noiſe as waked <hi>Marwoud. Who's there</hi> (cry'd he.) <hi>Your Friend.</hi> (ſaid Sir <hi>Francis) I'm glad to ſee you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live. How is it with Polydor?</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woud was amaz'd to hear him ask ſo pertinent a Queſtion, not apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how he ſhould know any thing of their laſt diſpute. <hi>I think Sir</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>Polydor is as well, if not better than I am: I'm ſure his Fortune was. But in the name of wonder how came you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with our Difference?</hi> Ariadne <hi>when you were gone, was fearful of what might enſue on what ſhe had ſaid to you,</hi> (reply'd Sir Francis) <hi>and could not reſt till ſhe had told me where you were gone,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:153254:63"/>
which brought us all to Town this Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning by ten a Clock, in hopes to prevent what I ſee is already too ſeverely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed. Ay alas!</hi> (cry'd Marwoud) <hi>with too ſevere Succeſs on his ſide; Curſe on this weak Arm, that could not reach his Heart. I am heartily glad it did not</hi> (reply'd the Knight,) <hi>for I ſhould cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly have loſt a dear Siſter had it been ſo, that either of you had fallen. O no!</hi> (interrupted Marwoud) <hi>had the wretched</hi> Marwoud <hi>falln as low as Hell, what had that concern'd the Adorable</hi> Ariadne! <hi>I muſt confeſs</hi> (added he with a ſcornful Smile:) <hi>if the moſt Accompliſh'd, and thrice happy</hi> Polydor <hi>had Died; 'twere enough to have broken any Ladys heart. 'Twere enough indeed</hi> (anſwered Ariadnes Brother) <hi>to have broken my Siſters heart, had you Kill'd her Husband on her Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count. How!</hi> (interrupted Marwoud in a great Conſternation) <hi>is ſhe then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Married to him after all this? after the Letter ſhe ſhew'd me, to perſwade me of the Contrary! 'Tis e'en ſo after all</hi> (reply'd Sir Francis.) <hi>And you ought not to be be troubled, if I deſire you to
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:153254:63"/>
receive him always as your friend. I may be Civil to him</hi> (anſwered Marwoud,) <hi>but I fear I ſhall never really love him. In ſhort</hi> (added he) <hi>I ſhall hardly ever en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to ſee him again. Come! Come</hi> (ſaid Sir Francis) <hi>this is not like a Man of Honour: I muſt and will have you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly Reconcil'd. That's as time ſhall try</hi> (reply'd Marwoud,) <hi>but at preſent it appears to me as impoſſible, as it is to recall Yeſterday. O!</hi> (cry'd Sir Francis) <hi>This is only the Effect of your late Animoſity. But</hi> (purſu'd he) <hi>pray make haſt and recover, that you may reſtore my Friend again to my Arms. You may come to my Houſe Conveniently enough in a Chair: but I would not have you be too haſty to leave your Chamber. I'le ſend</hi> Ariadne <hi>to Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit you in the Afternoon. In the mean time take care of your ſelf.</hi> Saying ſo he left him without expecting his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, and went home.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Marwoud</hi> did not at all like the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement his Friend made him, of bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Siſter to Viſit him: But he conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derd, he ſhou'd at ſometime or other be forc'd to ſee her, unleſs he cou'd altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:153254:64"/>
reſolve to forbear Converſing with her Brother, which made him put him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into the beſt Poſture he cou'd to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive her that Afternoon.</p>
            <p>Mean while <hi>Polydor</hi> far'd a great deal better for he cou'd make ſhift to walk, with the help of a Cane, and the Wound in his left Arm was ſcarce of any pain to him. Yet he thought it not altogether neceſſary to leave his Chamber for a day or two; which oblig'd him to ſend for his three old Companions whom he uſed ſo conſtantly to meet at <hi>Lockets</hi> or one Gaming-houſe or other. They came according to Summons; and expreſſed ſome little kind of trouble for that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Accident, which he told 'em was a fall from his Horſe. To play they went as briskly as at the Groom-Porters: And <hi>Polydor</hi>'s Hand held in moſt luckily! There was indeed ſome reaſon it ſhould, for, he Treated 'em very largely and generouſly with Wine and cold Meats.</p>
            <p>While they were thus throwing away their Money and Time, <hi>Ariadne</hi> accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied only with <hi>Miranda,</hi> came to ſee her Maim'd Souldier <hi>Marwood.</hi> Which, I
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:153254:64"/>
believe was no little ſatisfaction to her, finding him no worſe: For, ſhe conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded her <hi>Polydor</hi>'s Caſe was not ſo dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous; having heard as much from her Brother at Dinner. <q>Madam, (<hi>ſaid</hi> Marwoud <hi>to her</hi>) you do me too much Honour, and your ſelf too great a trouble in this Viſit; but, perhaps, 'tis a pleaſure to you to ſee me thus vanquiſh'd by the Man you had made your Husband, notwithſtanding the endeavours you uſed to diſguiſe it to me. You miſtake Sir (<hi>reply'd</hi> Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adne) if it be any pleaſure to me to ſee you in this Condition: 'tis be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, I hope it is much worſe with <hi>Polydor,</hi> for, I have already had time enough to repent my haſty Marriage with a Man of his mean Fortunes, and hateful Humours: And I come now to give you the opportunity of reven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging yourſelf and me too. But firſt, pray give me a particular Relation of your Duel.</q>
            </p>
            <p>He did ſo, with much uneaſineſs; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd when he came to that part of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tory; <q>How! (<hi>ſaid</hi> Ariadne) Had
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:153254:65"/>
you the ill fortune to be twice diſarm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by him! Yes <hi>(Madam, reply'd he vehemently)</hi> I had that damn'd con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded ill fortune, for, I am certain it was not through my want of Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution that it ſucceeded ſo well with him. I dont ſuſpect it was <hi>(anſwer'd ſhe)</hi> But I come now to pour Balſom into your Wounds; I mean thoſe of your mind; promiſe me but ſecrecy and truth! 'Tis neither Treaſon nor Murther I dare aſſure you. Let me know it I beſeech you <hi>(ſaid he gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily)</hi> I will attempt it; notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I have been unfortunate on your behalf in this laſt Enterpriſe. Alas (<hi>ſaid</hi> Ariadne) 'tis the eaſieſt thing imaginable, there's not the leaſt ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of danger in it. But you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe Fidelity, and Secrecy ſo much as to my Brother? For Heavens ſake do not doubt me! <hi>(Madam, ſaid he.)</hi> I will not (<hi>continu'd</hi> Ariadne) your Province then is to lay an Action o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Ten Thouſand Pounds on <hi>Polydor,</hi> in any bodies name, under pretence tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Debt was Contracted before
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:153254:65"/>
Marry'd him, manage this as cunning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as Revenge can inſtruct you; and <hi>I</hi> doubt not but to be rid of an Husband for ſome time, if not for ever! For, he not being us'd to a Priſon may the ſooner take the infection of it and die; I have been told that there is no Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon about Town but has a peculiar Diſtemper belonging to it. Ha! (<hi>cry'd</hi> Marwou'd) This is pretty well deſign'd! Let me alone <hi>(Madam)</hi> to Execute it. I'le about it the firſt thing I do, aſſoon as <hi>I</hi> can go abroad, and I am perſuaded, it will not a little Contribute to the Cure of the wound he was pleaſed to beſtow on me.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ariadne</hi> thanked him for the readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with which he embrac'd her Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions; and after a little other diſcourſe of things not altogether material to their Circumſtances; ſhe took <hi>Miranda</hi> with her and left him to reflect on this Bleſſed Opportunity ſhe had given him, of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in ſome meaſure revenged on a Man whom now he mortally hated.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:153254:66"/>With great impatience, he lingred out a Week: And when he ventur d out o' Doors, the firſt thing he did, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he had returned any of thoſe Viſits Sir <hi>Francis</hi> was pleaſed to make to him in his Chamber, was to enter an Action of Ten Thouſand Pounds againſt <hi>Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor</hi> in <hi>Wood-ſtreet</hi> Compter, at the Suit of Sir <hi>Tenacious Heedy:</hi> The next was to learn when he went into the City, which he heard would be within two days. He made a Viſit to him on the very day he was going, and offered him his Company into the City which was very kindly embraced by <hi>Polydor.</hi> Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens! How Sollicitous and induſtrious is malice, to compaſs its deviliſh ends! And how eaſily is an honeſt man decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved!</p>
            <p>The unwilling <hi>Polydor</hi> takes Coach immediately with his treacherous friend for the <hi>Sun-Tavern</hi> behind the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change,</hi> where he had engaged to meet ſome Friends; but they were no ſooner gotten within <hi>Ludgate</hi> e're the Coach was ſtopped by half a dozen Officers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to that Bleſſed place I told you
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:153254:66"/>
on before; who preſently ſeiz'd on both their Swords, and wou'd have hall'd <hi>Polydor</hi> out, had he not calmly ask'd 'em what they meant, and promiſed to make no reſiſtance if they cou'd ſhew any Authority for what they did. One of 'em told him, he had an Action a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, and wou'd ſhew him the Warrant, aſſoon as they came to any Tavern, that he ſhou'd name; and withal, like the reſt of the wheedling treacherous Fraternity promis'd him all the Civility imaginable, provided he wou'd obey the Kings Law. Well (ſaid he) let the Coach-man drive to <hi>Fowlers</hi> at the Half-Moon. The Raſcals lik'd that well enough, and very obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently trudg'd along by the Coach ſides till they came to the place afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Marwoud</hi> all along ſeem'd Amaz'd at this Accident, and appear'd as the moſt Concern'd man of the two. <hi>Now</hi> (ſaid <hi>Polydor</hi> to one of the Officers) <hi>at whoſe Suit am I a Priſoner? At the Suit of one Sir</hi> Tenacious Heedy (reply'd the Raſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal) <hi>here's the Warrant Sir, you may read
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:153254:67"/>
it if you pleaſe. Certainly friend</hi> (ſaid Polydor) <hi>you are miſtaken, though I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs I find my name here, but may there not be more of my name than my ſelf think you? for upon my Reputation, I never ſo much as heard of Sir</hi> Tenacious —<hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils name till this time! Pray what is he? A rich Merchant</hi> (anſwered one of the Furies) <hi>and belongs to the</hi> Eaſt-India <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany. Then be ſatisfied</hi> (ſaid Polydor,) <hi>I never had Trading with any of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion in my Life. No Sir that may be</hi> (return'd one of the Goblins) <hi>for, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it is a Debt contracted by your Lady. O damn'd Impoſtor!</hi> (cry'd Marwoud on a ſuddain, who had inſtructed this Rogue before.) <hi>It muſt be ſo I am confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, if the Officers have not miſtaken you for another. 'Tis impoſſible we ſhould Sir,</hi> (ſaid one of 'em.) <hi>This Adverſary was with us when he took Coach at to ther end of the Town, and told us this Gentleman was the Debter. Dear</hi> Harpies (ſaid Polydor Smiling,) <hi>How could you for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear your Prey ſo long! O Sir!</hi> (reply'd one.) <hi>you were out of our Territories till you came within</hi> Temple Bar, <hi>where yet
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:153254:67"/>
we did not think our ſelves ſecure enough of you, becauſe of the Templars, and ſome deſperate Blades that we might have met with in</hi> Fleet-ſtreet. <hi>You have reaſon Sir</hi> (ſaid Polydor ſmiling) <hi>I think here within your Dominions 'tis a matter of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, at leaſt for a Gentleman to draw his Sword in his own defence: It ſcares your whining Zealots out of the little Senſe they had. Beſides they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways apprehenſive of their own Guilt, and fear the Puniſhment they might reaſonab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expect from the Sword, for their Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious, Seditious and mutinous Endeavours againſt the Royal Prerogative. I'le tell you</hi> (continued he all in a flame, not ſo much for his own Circumſtances, as with Zeal for his Prince.) <q>I will not be Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner within theſe wicked Walls, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this City, in whoſe Great Streets and higheſt Places, the beſt of Kings. (O helliſh Riddle!) That Glorious Martyr for the Liberty of his People, was proclaim'd a Traitor! I ſay, I will not be confin'd to herd one Week to amend with 'em, leſt I get the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; at leaſt if a Hundred pounds
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:153254:68"/>
will remove me to the <hi>Kings-Bench</hi> I will not. — Why the Devil could not my Kt. Merchant Adverſary have taken me at our end of the Town? Was there a Neceſſity that I muſt be brought hither to this Stage, where the factious Schiſmaticks are playing the old Gaim again with ſome of the ſame Cards, only the Knaves are all Chang'd! where little Machiaville is playing his Pranks! A worthy Puſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed! — But there are Dogs that may Worry him at laſt.</q> While he rav'd thus; and <hi>Marwoud</hi> walk'd frown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about the Room. The Officers you may be confident were not Idle, they had top'd off a matter of Seven or Eight Bottles of Canary, and devour'd the beſt part of two Neats-Tongues. At laſt one of them beg'd leave of his Gut, to ſpeak to <hi>Polydor. Well Sir</hi> (ſaid he! <hi>What do you propoſe? will you ſend for Bail? Send for a Whore Sir; I'le go to Priſon,</hi> (cry'd Polydor) <hi>O fy!</hi> (ſaid Marwoud) <hi>do not think on't! If I thought my Bail would be taken, I would offer you my Service. O by no means dear Friend!</hi>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:153254:68"/>
(replyed Polydor, Embracing the Snake) <hi>I am reſolved to ſtand it out my ſelf. Then</hi> (Interrupted one of the Troubleſome Attendants,) <hi>Since your Worſhip will go to Priſon; yet, however you ſhall not go into the Compter, but if you pleaſe you may Lie at a Priſon Houſe over againſt it, till you have Compoſed this Buſineſs. No Sir I'le go to the Compter upon my word,</hi> (reply'd Polydor.) <hi>Indeed you ſhall not, nor muſt not,</hi> (ſaid Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woud,) who wiſhed nothing more in the World than that he might Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> there.</p>
            <p>What Exquiſite Miſcheif may be done with the face of Friendſhip! <hi>I am ſorry</hi> (anſwered the true and faithful Polydor) <hi>I muſt be obſtinate, but I have ſome Reaſons for it.</hi> Now (the Duce take me) If I know what Reaſon he cou'd have for it: Unleſs it were to avoid the Extortions of a Sponging Houſe; which nevertheleſs, had he been in the <hi>Compter</hi> ſo often as I; he wou'd have endur'd, rather than have ſeen the inſide on't. <q>Indeed Sir, I wou'd not adviſe you to go into the <hi>Compter;</hi> you will
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:153254:69"/>
find it very diſagreeable to your hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour: The Priſoners there will be all ready to tear you in pieces for Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, (ſaid one of the Officers.) I ſhall prevent 'em (Sir) for I'le pay it (ſaid <hi>Polydor.</hi>) Nay, if you pleaſe to like it Sir; <hi>Reply'd one of 'em whoſe Brother in Law kept a Sponging Houſe</hi>) you may go into the Priſon. But there's the Turnkeys Fee, and ſeven ſhillings a Week for a dirty, dark hole, with Cobwebs about your Bed inſtead of Curtains. When if you wou'd be perſuaded (Sir) you may lie in as good a Bed as my Lord Mayor, and have what Meat and Drink you pleaſe, and Dreſs'd how you pleaſe, beſides, the Liberty of walking down into the Dining Room. But I muſt pay for it Sir (Interrupted <hi>Polydor</hi>) I ſhall have there my Landlord, who (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps) Drinks like a <hi>Dane,</hi> Cringes like a <hi>French man,</hi> Grins like my Lady's Monkey, when he ſees Money coming; but if that be not ready, he looks as ſurly as a Butchers Dog, or as the Butcher himſelf, who is the
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:153254:69"/>
rudeſt Beaſt of the two! His Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany I ſhall never fail of, then one or two of your Worſhips will come to Viſit me, three or four times a day and make me as uneaſy as this Sir <hi>Boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by</hi> that Arreſts me will be when he hears I'm gone over to the <hi>Kings-Bench;</hi> — No Sir; I am bound for the Compter; there I'le treat my fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Priſoners, that want a Bottle of Wine and a luſty Joint of Meat! 'Twill be well beſtow'd.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>How long is it ſince you have had ſo good knowledge of theſe Houſes you have deſcrib'd? (ſaid <hi>Marwoud</hi>) I hope you never were confin'd till now. I never was indeed (<hi>replyed</hi> Polydor.) But I have viſited ſome of my acquaintance in ſuch like places ſeveral times. Well Sir ſince you are ſo obſtinate, and will not be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail'd on for your own good; (ſaid <hi>one of the Serjeants</hi>) you ſhall e'en have your humour, but I fear you'l repent it. I ſhall not however ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint you with my Penitence if I do, (<hi>anſwer'd</hi> Polydor,) So, let's know
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:153254:70"/>
what's to pay; that I may be gone to my Palace. Dear Friend (<hi>continued he, ſpeaking to</hi> Marwoud) oblige me ſo far as to enquire into this buſineſs for me; and ſee what muſt be done in't, and give your ſelf a little farther trouble to ſend <hi>Harry, Will,</hi> or <hi>Tom,</hi> any one of 'em or all of 'em together to me, by to Morrow Noon. I will not fail (<hi>replyed</hi> Marwoud) Can I do you any better Service? I am ſorry at the Heart that I muſt leave you: Yet if my Company may add any thing to your ſatisfaction, command my ſtay with you as long as you pleaſe, and where you will; I'le put off all buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſo I may any way contribute to the eaſing of your Misfortunes. O by no means (<hi>anſwer'd</hi> Polydor <hi>again, Embracing his Evil Angel</hi>) I cannot ſuffer it. I know you will be at no great eaſe in ſuch a place, which will but encreaſe my trouble.</q>
            </p>
            <p>As they had ended this Diſcourſe, the Drawer brought up a Bill of about eight and twenty Shillings which theſe Vermin had devour'd in leſs than three hours
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:153254:70"/>
time, and yet the Dogs were ſo greedy that they were craving ſtill; they were for Money for waiting! (with ſo many Plagues to them as they drank Glaſſes of Wine!) <hi>Money for waiting!</hi> (cry d <hi>Polydor) yes; let them pay you that ſet you awork.</hi> They look'd a little ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; but ſaid no more, becauſe they ſaw their Pay-Maſter in the Room; who wou'd needs pay the Reckoning out of the extraordinary ſatisfaction he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd in <hi>Polydor's</hi> Affliction: But <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woud</hi> pretended, it was for fear <hi>Polydor</hi> ſhou'd have occaſion for Money, in his ill Circumſtances.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Polydor</hi> took leave of him to go to his Enchanted Caſtle, with a Reſolution worthy an Hero who makes ſuch deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Adventures! He was attended only by four of the Giants Warders. The other two ſtayd with <hi>Marwoud</hi> till they had ſqueezed three Guinneys out of him. He charged them when he was going to look ſtrictly to their Priſoner and not to allow him any liberty, that they might lawfully deny him. They promiſed to be very obſervant of his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:153254:71"/>
and left him to go homewards without his Companion; for my part, I wiſh <hi>Polydor</hi> had gone homeward with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him, and had left him to keep his Bed warm in the Compter! But hang't! 'Tis ridiculous to wiſh Impoſſibilities! Well! Let the Treacherous <hi>Marwou'd</hi> e'en trudge on! Wee'l return to my good friend <hi>Polydor;</hi> who by this time had enter'd the Fort and pay'd all Dutys belonging to it.</p>
            <p>All the reſt of the poor Enchanted Souls look'd upon him, as the wretched Ghoſts in Hell did on <hi>Hercules</hi> and <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeus</hi> whom they were in hopes came to deliver 'em; and truly if <hi>Polydor</hi> did not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together enlarge their Bodies, yet he did much encreaſe their Commons, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his ſtay there. Inſomuch, that they all eſteem'd him their Deliverer from a lingring ſort of Famin! For he dayly gave Alms to the meaneſt: You may ſee Providence in this now! For had he not been ſent thither, many a poor Soul might have Periſh'd of Hunger and Thirſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:153254:71"/>His Charity to all, and his kind eaſy Converſation with the moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nferiour and Miſerable Creature there was ſo ſignal, that the Keepers took particular notice of it, and told him, after he had been there two Days and ſome Hours, by way of Complement as I ſuppoſe they inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it; that, <q>They ſhou'd be mighty ſorry to loſe his Company; at leaſt <hi>(they added)</hi> the Priſoners would have no ſmall cauſe to Lament his Depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, tho they ought to wiſh it for his ſake. He Smil'd, and told 'em, 'He thought he was oblig'd to it as he was a Man, if not as a Chriſtian and a Fellow Sufferer.</q>
            </p>
            <p>They had more diſcourſe as they walk'd, at the end of which, a Jolly, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Soul, (and ſo you wou'd judge by the Ruddy Complexion of his Face) one who had no ſmall Authority there, Invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him into the Lodge; telling him, and that truly, that it was the ſweeter place of the two. He Embrac'd his kind proffer; and to ſhew he was not ungrateful for favours ſent for half a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen Bottles of good Clarret from <hi>Matt.
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:153254:72"/>
Fowlers,</hi> and beſpoke two good ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial Diſhes of Meat for his Friend, his ſelf and the Priſoners.</p>
            <p>As they were drinking a Glaſs or two before Dinner; in came thoſe two Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers that ſtay'd behind with <hi>Marwoud,</hi> who had heard of his Generoſity to thoſe in the Houſe, and of his Civility to every Body, and who perceiv'd he had Money enough; <q>O (<hi>cry'd</hi> Polydor, <hi>looking on his Friend in Authority.</hi>) Theſe are ſome of the Gentlemen that brought me hither to be acquainted with you. Sirs! Pray walk in and drink with us <hi>(continu'd he, to the Officers)</hi> They were eaſily prevail'd on, and ſate 'em down:</q>
            </p>
            <p>After a Glaſs or two had gone about; (ſaid the Serjeant) <q>I wonder, Sir, No body has been with you yet! Ay (<hi>ſaid</hi> Polydor) 'tis ſomething ſtrange! But I doubt not, my Friend whom you ſaw with me t'other day, is buſie in getting my Liberty; and means I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, to ſurprize me with it; yet I admire he has not ſent ſome other Friends to me whom I expected to ſee
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:153254:72"/>
here the next day after my Confine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. You have been very patient, Sir, <hi>(ſaid the Officer)</hi> I don't hear that you have ſent to any Friend yet. No, no, I need not trouble my ſelf, I'm ſure (<hi>reply'd</hi> Polydor) my Friend is labouring for my eaſe. You mean Squire <hi>Marwoud, (anſwer'd the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeant.)</hi> I do ſo (<hi>ſaid</hi> Polydor.) I can then aſſure you <hi>(continu'd the Officers)</hi> that he is indeavouring, labouring all the ways imaginable to keep you in a Priſon all the days of your Life. How Sir (<hi>Interrupted</hi> Polydor, <hi>ſtrangly Surpris'd!</hi>) what, do you know what you ſay! Ay, ay, Sir, <hi>(ſaid the other Serjeant)</hi> and Il ſwear it, Sir; and two Witneſſes are enough to caſt a Suit at Common Law. That may be Sir, (<hi>anſwer'd</hi> Polydor) but a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Witneſſes will hardly make me ſuſpect my Friend. But pray, what ground have you for what you ſay? Why, Sir <hi>(replyed one of 'em)</hi> ſince we have found you here among us a Civil, Obliging, and Charitable Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; I'l tell you the whole truth, which
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:153254:73"/>
I will Swear to, and ſo will my Friend there. Be aſſur'd then, that it was he who ſet you for three days together, till the very day he ſecur'd you in the Coach where we took you. I dare ſwear it before any Magiſtrate in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, (Interrupted t'other Serjeant.)</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t may be ſo Sir, (<hi>replyed</hi> Polydor.) Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides <hi>(purſu'd the Serjeant)</hi> I'm ſure we had three Guinneys of him. If this be true; (<hi>cry'd</hi> Polydor) I am a very unfortunate Fellow, indeed! For, the loſs of a Friend grieves me a thouſand times more than my Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment. But <hi>(continu'd he)</hi> did he ſay, I ow'd him any Money? No Sir <hi>(replyed the Serjeant)</hi> he told us, the Debt was real, and Contracted by a Lady whom you had lately Marry'd. This is all a Riddle to me! <hi>ſaid</hi> Polydor, But I thank you Gentlemen for your Information. I find I am made the ſport of Fortune of late. I was a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Fellow and at Liberty once.—But now— Well! — Gentlemen, your Servant.—I thank you for this Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. — Why Sir, will you be going
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:153254:73"/>
already, <hi>(ſaid he who Invited him into the Lodge)</hi> Dinner is juſt a coming I believe, by this time. Be pleas'd then Gentlemen (<hi>reply'd</hi> Polydor) to feed heartily when it do's come; and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite ſome of your Friends in the Houſe to eat with you, that want it moſt, at leaſt be pleaſed to ſend 'em what you think fit, for my part, I care not for eating. I muſt mind my own buſineſs I ſee. And pray let me entreat the favour of you, to let me have a care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Meſſenger ſent to me; and you ſhall command me as much another time, if I ever am in a Capacity of ſerving you. Ay Sir, wee'l be ſure to ſend you a very honeſt Fellow <hi>(an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd one of 'em)</hi> but we are ſorry you will not Dine, when you have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready given order for Meat. I thank you Sir (<hi>ſaid</hi> Polydor) I have buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of greater concern than Dining, once more your Servant.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The Gate was ſoon open'd to him, you may believe; and to his dark Apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he went directly. Where after two or three hearty Sighs; he began.
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:153254:74"/>
               <q>How ſhou'd <hi>Marwoud</hi> come acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with my <hi>Ariadne!</hi> How came ſhe to employ him! And how durſt he undertake ſo baſe a thing as to betray his Friend! Yet—what made him fight me for the Ring and the Gold! What Title had he to either of 'em. 'Tis a ſtrange Myſtery, profound and dark! And I am loſt in't. He muſt know my Falſe <hi>Ariadne,</hi> if he did really betray me to this place, that's certain, <hi>Ariadne</hi> did I call her? A very Improper Name it is (methinks) for her: For,—ſhe has led me into a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byrinth! I ſee, all <hi>Ariadnes</hi> are not of the ſame humour. Her Name ſake bravely led her Lover forth, ſpite of a Cruel Father! Ventur'd all, and loſt her ſelf at laſt for a falſe Man! When I Diſarm'd and naked of deceit, have got into the Labyrinth, and met the Monſter. So much for Honeſty! So much for Truth! But O! How much for raſh Credulity! Had I been practic'd in the World's great Arts, Treaſon, Rebellion, and Hypocriſy. cou'd I have nos'd my Prince, and to
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:153254:74"/>
his Teeth have told him that his Power was but painted; cou'd I have ſworn a Maid into belief, of any feig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Love, and when I had enjoy'd, have thrown the Rifl'd, Broad, Blown Flow'r behind me; cou'd I, in my Dear Friends Boſom lying, pierce it to reach his Heart; and after all, cheat Heaven with pretended Piety, ſerve God with lift up Eyes and diſmal tone; but Heart of Marble, ſinking down to Hell, then I had been a Glorious De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil! Then, my Prince might ha' been pitty'd, the loſt Maid have Fruitleſs Tears with my Friends unrevenged Bloud. They'd only ſuffer'd.—O! No; I miſtake: They had been Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed (perhaps) and with their Sighs have blaſted all my hopes of future Bliſs, and blown me down to Hell; for Heaven ſees, and is not to be mock'd.</q>
            </p>
            <p>He fetch'd another deep Sigh at the end of this long Sermon, and threw him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf on his Bed: Within a little after the Fellow came to him to know what Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice he had to command him. He roſe
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:153254:75"/>
and diſpatch'd him away to his three Gaming Friends; and being then ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what tir'd with Grief, and not having yet ſlept well in his new Lodging, he fel into a ſlumber for two or three hours.</p>
            <p>About which time the Meſſenger re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd with his three Friends. He was almoſt out o' Countenance when he ſaw 'em; and hardly knew how to receive 'em. At laſt (<hi>ſaid</hi> Will,) <q>Why, how now <hi>Polydor!</hi> What brought thee hither? E'en my own Folly (<hi>replyed</hi> Polydor) you will not pitty me when you hear it. However, I muſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe it to you, that you may give me your Advice; you muſt know then, I'am Marry'd.—Marry'd <hi>(cry'd all three, in a ſtrange Surprize)</hi> Ay, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry'd (<hi>continu'd</hi> Polydor) and to one of the moſt Beautiful Creatures breathing! One whom I wou'd not leave for the Empire of the World, were ſhe but really what ſhe ſeem'd. You appear Amaz'd at what I ſay <hi>(pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu'd he)</hi> but ſit ye down and I will relate you the whole Adventure; 'Tis pure Knight Errantry, that you muſt take
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:153254:75"/>
notice of before hand.</q> Then he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan and told 'em every Circumſtance till the very Minute that they came to him. They heard it with a great deal of Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Wonder, but with no little trouble for their Friends ſake. <q>I'm ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry (<hi>ſaid</hi> Will,) you are fallen into the hands of Sir <hi>Tenacious Heedy,</hi> I have heard he's a meer <hi>Jew</hi> to any Man that ows him Money. No, Pox on't! (<hi>cry'd</hi> Harry) Nothing troubles me but that he is Marry'd. And what's worſe (<hi>added</hi> Tom,) that he ſhou'd throw himſelf away without ever ſo much as asking the advice of any of his Friends! You ſee Friend (<hi>ſaid</hi> Harry) what comes of Weddings! Pox take me, if I can pitty you for the heart of me. Why were there not Wives enow in the Town of other Mens but you muſt needs get one of your own! And (<hi>added</hi> Will,) to believe a little Raſcally Lad in a matter of ſuch moment! A likely piece of buſineſs indeed, (<hi>cry'd</hi> Harry) that a Lady of twelve hundred a Year and ſome thouſands in Money and Jewels,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:153254:76"/>
ſhou'd diſpoſe of her ſelf on ſuch a Perſon as thine! There had been ſome reaſon; had ſome probability, that I might have had ſuch Fortune: I might juſtly expect it. Yes, from ſuch a Lady as <hi>Sycorax</hi> in the Tempeſt, with a Dowry of Enchanted Lands (<hi>cry'd</hi> Tom) which you may take Poſſeſſion of when you can diſcern 'em.—No, Faith, <hi>(continu'd he)</hi> to give the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil his due, <hi>Polydor</hi> has the advantage of us all, that way. Ay, (<hi>reply'd</hi> Harry) and to give the Devil his due, he's the ſilly'ſt Devil that ever I heard of! Come! You are Merry Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men at my Coſt, (<hi>interrupted</hi> Polydor) but this is nothing to my Liberty, this is no Advice; tho 'tis what I did really expect from you. Advice, (<hi>cry'd</hi> Harry) why prithee ſend for thy Wife <hi>Ariadne</hi> with her Clue, if thou know'ſt whither. I believe ſhe's gone to my <hi>Sycorax,</hi> for their Lands lie very near together. No, no, (<hi>interrupted</hi> Tom) I rather imag n <hi>Bacchus</hi> has taken her up too, into Heaven; he's an old Dog at <hi>Ariadne</hi>'s! You ſhall ſee he'l
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:153254:76"/>
fetch Sir <hi>Francis</hi>'s Siſter and all, ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Enough, enough of this! (<hi>cry'd</hi> Will, <hi>very ſoberly</hi>) Let's think what's to be done. Why; I'l tell you my opinion (<hi>reply'd</hi> Harry) I know a rich old Widow about three-ſcore, I'l ſend her to him, if he'l Marry her; ſo as Marrying brought him in, let it e'en fetch him out. Very ſeaſonable and wholſom Advice i' gad! (<hi>cry'd</hi> Tom) And then, 'tis but leaving her aſſoon as he gets out, as <hi>Ariadne</hi> has left him, and he may thus be quitts with Fortune. Y' are very pretty Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows truly (<hi>ſaid</hi> Polydor) But—It may fall to my ſhare to laugh at you, yet e'r I die. Ay, if your Spouſe ſhou'd prove a right Diamond and no Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit, (<hi>replyed</hi> Harry) you might laugh at us for laughing at you. In the mean time caſe your Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>en the other way, if you can, 'twill become you better. Come dear heart (<hi>ſaid</hi> Will <hi>to</hi> Polydor) Take no notice of theſe two Raſcals!—I'l do what lies in my Power to ſerve thee, upon my Soul! <hi>Polydor</hi> than<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'d him very obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gingly.</q>
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:153254:77"/>
               <q>Hark O! what Gravity! (<hi>cry'd</hi> Harry) As if it were not poſſible that we might be as ready to ſerve him with our Lives and Fortunes as your Worſhip; becauſe you talk and look ſo ſuperciliouſly, and we ſo freely! Well ſaid <hi>Harry! (cry'd</hi> Tom) What Do's the Rogue affront us! Away, ye Brace of Coxcombs! (<hi>replyed</hi> Will.) I don't accuſe ye of any Averſneſs to his Service. But, methinks, you ſhou'd have pleas'd your ſelves ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently with your raillery on him, by this time. Prithee, let's now be ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. Nay, for my part (<hi>anſwer'd</hi> Harry) I can be as ſerious as a Pick-Pocket at his buſineſs in a Church. And I (<hi>ſaid</hi> Tom) can be as ſerious as the Perſon! Well! And what's to be done now? I think it the beſt way (<hi>repl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d</hi> Will,) to remove him to the <hi>Fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> No (<hi>interrupted</hi> Polydor) I'le rather remove to the <hi>Kings-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ench,</hi> I have ſome acquaintance there already, beſides I have drank ſome Bottles with the Marſhal, who, I am confident, will give <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> all the Liberty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> may
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:153254:77"/>
with ſafety. I'l be ſure to Viſit you every day in Term time at leaſt. And wee'l make thee as welcom as we can, (<hi>cry'd</hi> Harry;) that is, thou ſhalt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver go over the Water ſober. Hang your <hi>Dutch</hi> Entertainments! (<hi>ſaid</hi> Polydor) I'm out of conceit of 'em. A Bleſſed Reformation, if it hold! (<hi>ſaid</hi> Tom.) It ſhall Sir (<hi>replyed</hi> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lydor.)</q>
            </p>
            <p>They had ſome farther diſcourſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the means of getting him over, which laſted about a quarter of an hour more, then they ſent for half a dozen Bottles of Clarret to the old Houſe, and a diſh of cold Chickens. By that time <hi>Polydor's</hi> Stomach was come to him. For, if ever you were a Priſoner, you may be ſenſible the ſight of a Friend or two there, revives a Man ſtrangely! He eat as heartily as he did on his Wedding day: And drank off his three Bumpers as he uſed to do, to the King, the Queen, and the Duke.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:153254:78"/>They ſtay'd with him till the Fatal Bell was rung, which commands every Priſoner cloſe to his Chamber, and all others abroad to their buſineſs. Here you might ſee one lugging two Guns (as they call 'em) which in plain <hi>Engliſh</hi> are two Pottle-Pots of Ale and Beer, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother following him with ſome <hi>Tobac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co,</hi> a Candle and Pipes. There a poor Soul with two or three Bottles of the Sheriffs Wine, <hi>Anglicè</hi> Fair Water; begging of another to fill his dirty Pipe with ſtinking Mundungus.</p>
            <p>I ſuppoſe, the miſerable Wretch was one of the Common-ſide. You may believe me, for I have lay'n in the Houſe ſome Nights my ſelf to my Sorrow; Nor is it any great matter of wonder, for a Man of my Circumſtances to have been a Priſoner: You know we are ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally ſpecial Poor. Well! There were a great many other Objects of Pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty beſides this Man, that a Curious Perſon wou'd have taken notice on. But <hi>Polydor</hi>'s Friends were none of that ſort, for they went out aſſoon as they cou'd perſuade the Turnkey to open
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:153254:78"/>
the Door. <hi>Polydor</hi> return'd to his Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and very contentedly went to Bed, where he ſlept ſoundly; for he had drank his ſhare with his Friends.</p>
            <p>Next Morning, he found himſelf in very good temper, and withal ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing inclinable to Rhiming. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he ſet Pen to Paper and made,</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="text">
                        <head>An Attempt, in <hi>Pindarique,</hi> On the Bleſſings of <hi>Adverſity.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <lg n="1">
                           <head>I.</head>
                           <l>THE Juſt and Brave unmov'd appear,</l>
                           <l>In Storms where meaner Souls do ſhrink,</l>
                           <l>And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>v'n beneath themſelves do ſink;</l>
                           <l>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nable Miſeries leaſt weight to bear!</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="146" facs="tcp:153254:79"/>Or, if with Wealth and Honour Crown'd,</l>
                           <l>No room within their narrow Heart is found,</l>
                           <l>To entertain the Bluſt'ring Gueſt;</l>
                           <l>But ſwelling with the Bubble ſtraight they burſt!</l>
                           <l>They in Adverſe or Proſp'rous Fate alike are Curs'd!</l>
                           <l>When, the great Soul does ſcarce admit</l>
                           <l>The Fawning Paraſite:</l>
                           <l>Or, if he does; 'tis lock'd within his Breaſt:</l>
                           <l>Nor ſuffers him to play his part,</l>
                           <l>Within the Cabinet of his Heart,</l>
                           <l>But ſlighted, in the Ante-Chamber let's him ſit.</l>
                           <l>An equal mind in different Fates he bears:</l>
                           <l>The one he neither Courts, nor t'other fears;</l>
                           <l>Nor is with this puff'd up, nor that depreſs'd:</l>
                           <l>But in himſelf alone is ever Bleſs'd.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg n="2">
                           <pb n="147" facs="tcp:153254:79"/>
                           <head>II.</head>
                           <l>Ambition, Anger, Avarice and Luſt,</l>
                           <l>With other Paſſions of the Mind,</l>
                           <l>The Gen'rous Soul in Reaſons Chain does bind;</l>
                           <l>And as his Captives at his Feet does thruſt,</l>
                           <l>Tho Fierce and Great to Slavery do's bring;</l>
                           <l>Here <hi>Nero</hi>'s Tyrant li's and <hi>Alexander's</hi> King!</l>
                           <l>When the baſe Wretch is his Slaves, Slave;</l>
                           <l>Which, like a Conqu'ring Prince, do's brave</l>
                           <l>The reaſon Heaven to defend him gave:</l>
                           <l>It's Throne <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurps, and do's affect to Raign,</l>
                           <l>Lord of the ſtrongeſt Caſtles, both the Heart and Brain!</l>
                           <l>And now grows Inſolent and Lewd:</l>
                           <l>Revels, and mingles with the pureſt of his Bloud!</l>
                           <l>Do's his beſt Faculties controul;</l>
                           <l>And wou'd debauch his chaſter Soul!</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="148" facs="tcp:153254:80"/>At leaſt miſleads it for a Space;</l>
                           <l>Then leaves it naked to diſgrace!</l>
                           <l>The Man who thus is by his Paſſions ſway'd,</l>
                           <l>O'r Beaſts ſhou'd wiſh to Rule, never to be obey'd!</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg n="3">
                           <head>III.</head>
                           <l>Bleſs'd is the Man whom Heaven do's not try,</l>
                           <l>With guilded Apples of Proſperity;</l>
                           <l>Sweet to the Taſt and Beauteous to the Eye,</l>
                           <l>But Rotten at the Coar and Poyſon to the Heart!</l>
                           <l>But thrice bleſs'd he who can reject</l>
                           <l>The proffer'd Pleaſure of the Bait;</l>
                           <l>Who ſees the future dire effect,</l>
                           <l>If overcome by the Deceit.</l>
                           <l>Loſing the Pleaſure he avoids the deadly Smart!</l>
                           <l>But thrice and four times Bleſs'd is he</l>
                           <l>Whom Heaven try's with Miſery,</l>
                           <l>And hardly Cloaths with Rags of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty!</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="149" facs="tcp:153254:80"/>Who ſilently do's bear his Fate</l>
                           <l>And is contented in his loweſt State.</l>
                           <l>Inur'd to Grief and ſad Miſchance,</l>
                           <l>Surely, tho ſlow tow'rd Heav'n he do's advance</l>
                           <l>Treading on Thorns the way to Bliſs!</l>
                           <l>Adverſity the greateſt Bleſſing is!</l>
                           <l>And nothing than Proſperity is worſe!</l>
                           <l>Proſperity ill-us'd, the greateſt Curſe.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg n="4">
                           <head>IV.</head>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Job</hi>'s Tempter, ſure, miſtook the way,</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Job</hi>'s Virtue to betray!</l>
                           <l>Or, rather, the <hi>All-Merciful</hi> deny'd</l>
                           <l>That his Beloved Servant ſhould be try'd</l>
                           <l>By heaping Riches, ſo to teach him Pride.</l>
                           <l>Hard'ned in Grief and Plagues his Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue grew;</l>
                           <l>Steel'd it became, Temptation-Proof it was!</l>
                           <l>The deadlyeſt Darts which on him <hi>Satan</hi> threw,</l>
                           <l>His Body pierced, but could no farther paſs.</l>
                           <l>
                              <pb n="150" facs="tcp:153254:81"/>His Patience to his Tempter gave more Pain,</l>
                           <l>Than all <hi>Job</hi> did ſuſtein!</l>
                           <l>And he was Plagu'd, and he was ſhot in vain!</l>
                           <l>When (Lo!) Th' Almighty from Above,</l>
                           <l>With Eyes with Pitty flowing and with Love,</l>
                           <l>Beheld the Afflicted Man, as weak he lay,</l>
                           <l>Buryed in Aſhes on the Ground:</l>
                           <l>Vouch'dſafe to Parley with this thing of Clay!</l>
                           <l>Taught him to know himſelf and made him ſound.</l>
                           <l>And for the Miſeries which he had ſhar'd,</l>
                           <l>Gave him a Seven-fold Reward.</l>
                           <l>Teach me then, Heaven, to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand</l>
                           <l>The heavieſt ſtroke of Sorrows hand!</l>
                           <l>That, to my ſelf brought home, I may</l>
                           <l>The Obedience which I owe thee ever pay!</l>
                        </lg>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:153254:81"/>He had ſcarce made an end before an under-Officer of the Houſe came to tell him there was a Gentleman and a Lady below that would ſpeak with him. He was not a little Surprized at it, not ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining what Lady ſhould come to give him a Viſit in ſuch a place, unleſs it were his own Siſter. However he bid the Fellow lead them up. He did ſo. And <hi>Polydor</hi> then was much more amazed than before, when he ſaw his own falſe <hi>Ariadne,</hi> as he thought her, led in by <hi>Marwoud</hi> the Treacherous. They ſtood ſtaring on one another a pretty while, e'r either of 'em could ſpeak. But <hi>Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor</hi> was in a ſtrange Perplexity! You would have thought he had been in a Feaver by his Face; he would fain have been angry and have rail'd at her, but when he beheld her Beauty, he was no more able to do't, than I am to fight a Whale in the water! And that is not very probable; for I can Swim no more than a Mill-ſtone:</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:153254:82"/>
               <hi>Heavens!</hi> (cry'd <hi>Polydor,</hi> pulling his Hat over his Eyes, and walking from her in a great deal of haſt) <hi>Art thou come now thy ſelf to torment me! Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Woman! Go! Take that Treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Man into thy deceitful Boſom, make as much of him as your falſe Heart will give you leave. And thou</hi> Marwou'd, <hi>Faithleſs Man! Embrace, Embrace the</hi> Syren! <hi>Go together! And betray one another into a groundleſs and vain Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of each others mutual Affection! Shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Man</hi> (continued he, looking fiercely on <hi>Marwoud) what unheard of Impudence has brought thee into my ſight, after thou haſt thus betrayed me! But what ill things dare not he do, that durſt betray his Friend!</hi> 
               <q>Why, this is very ſtrange (<hi>Interrupted</hi> Marwoud) what do you mean, <hi>Polydor?</hi>
               </q> 
               <hi>I mean to Cudgel thee</hi> (replyed <hi>Polydor,</hi> all in a Rage) <hi>for thou art not worthy of my Sword!</hi> 
               <q>O! fy! (<hi>interrupted</hi> Ariadne) Is it thus you Treat your Friends.</q> 
               <hi>Peace,</hi> Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren! Hypocrite! Fair Devil! Peace! (cryed <hi>Polydor) Thy Breath and Looks are Infectious!</hi> 
               <q>Good Heaven! (<hi>ſaid</hi>
                  <pb n="153" facs="tcp:153254:82"/>
Ariadne <hi>weeping</hi>) How have I deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved this!</q> 
               <hi>Ah Crocodile!</hi> (cryed <hi>Polydor,</hi> with an angry Smile) <hi>I confeſs thou haſt not deſerved that I ſhould ſpeak to thee! But—admire now the ſweetneſs of my Temper! That I can vouchſafe to tell thee I am angry with thee: And that I have much reaſon to hate thee: O! Would I could! On what Errant has Hell ſent thee to me now? Or, rather what greater Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction is Heaven yet pleaſed to try me with!—Come! I'le be tame. And gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tly will confeſs thy Power to thee. Wert thou but half ſo Virtuous as Fair; and I a thouſand times more Rich and Happy, than now I am miſerable: I'd kneel to get one Smile of thee. But —thou art</hi>— <q>Hold! (<hi>interrupted</hi> Ariadne) And hear my Buſineſs firſt; e're you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to Judgment of me! I come to offer you all that I have; and were it Twenty Thouſand times more, I would lay it all at your Feet; I have brought this Gentleman, my Friend; who (it ſeems) has been long your Friend, however you are willing to miſtake him now; him I have engag'd
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:153254:83"/>
to Compound the Debt with Sir <hi>Tena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious,</hi> and if he will not accept of our Propoſitions; he has procur'd another Gentleman his Friend to Bail you with him. She tells you truth <hi>Polydor (ſaid</hi> Marwoud) tho your Paſſion blinds, and will not let you ſee our kind In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions to ſerve you.</q> 
               <hi>And is it really true?</hi> (cry'd <hi>Polydor</hi>) 'Moſt certain, (<hi>replyed</hi> Ariadne.) <hi>Then Dam yee, Dam yee both,</hi> (cryed <hi>Polydor,</hi> furiouſly) <hi>What! Purchaſe my Liberty with the Proſtitution of your Body! I tell yee, tho you both conſulted to get me into this place; yet I'l make a ſhift to get out on't, without your Aid, Advice, or Money. And for thy part</hi> Marwoud (continued he) <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect I will thank thee moſt juſtly for thy In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry in delivering me into the hands of theſe People; who yet have uſed me more civilly than thou deſired'ſt I ſhould have been.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He then told him what he had heard from the Officers; while the other la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured with all the Cunning he had, to perſwade him, that he was abuſed by them, in that Diſcourſe: But all to no
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:153254:83"/>
purpoſe. <hi>Nay</hi> (ſaid <hi>Polydor) 'tis in vain to hope I ſhould believe thee true to me now; when thy very acquaintance with this Woman Lowdly Proclaims thy Guilt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>While they were arguing thus very hotly; <hi>Ariadne</hi> took up the Verſes and ſlipt 'em into her Pocket. At laſt they grew lowd; and then <hi>Polydor</hi> taking <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riadne</hi> by the hand, led her civilly out of the Room; but <hi>Marwoud</hi> he almoſt threw down Stairs; and immediately ſhut the Door to him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ariadne</hi> beg'd of him with all the earneſtneſs that might be, to open the Door to her; urging that ſhe had ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to diſcover to him that concerned the whole Quiet of his Life; but all in vain! He bid her be gone and come no more near him. She ſtill preſt to come in, and I believe would have made up all Differences had ſhe prevail'd; for ſhe was really very ſenſible that ſhe had been to blame, in treating him thus ſo long. But being ſtill denyed entrance, ſhe went away with a Reſolution to play him yet one other Trick e're ſhe undeceived him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="156" facs="tcp:153254:84"/>
               <hi>Marwoud</hi> was much out of humour, and in a great heat with <hi>Polydor,</hi> for folling him ſo baſely before his Miſtreſs; but he conſidered, there was no Sword to be drawn there; and beſides, his hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Rival was then Naked whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h ſtop'd the effects of his Indignation, for a time: Yet he could not forbear threatning him with Revenge, and that in the hearing of <hi>Ariadne.</hi> Who told him, he need ſtudy no greater Revenge than what he had already; or at leaſt, than what he was like to have by her means.</p>
            <p>This pretty well appeaſed the affront<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Squire; and he waited on her home without ſo much as ever threatning <hi>Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor</hi> again.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Polydor,</hi> was a little diſturbed at this unſeaſonable Viſit; becauſe (perhaps) ſince the Fit had juſt ſeiz'd him, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to have gone on Rhiming, which their unexpected and unwiſhed for Company prevented. Being therefore ſomewhat diſcompoſed, he went to his Friend in the Lodge and deſired to drink a Glaſs of Wine with him; which was preſently permitted him; and they Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:153254:84"/>
together very plentifully and chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully.</p>
            <p>About 5. a Clock, as he was Drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Grace Cup, he was told that there was a Lady in a Coach at the Gate who asked for him, and the officious Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger had hardly ſaid the word, e're he ſaw <hi>Dorothea</hi> come in, whom he had all along miſtaken for Sir <hi>Francis</hi>'s Siſter <hi>Ariadne.</hi> She was attended by two Footmen, one of which was <hi>Polydor</hi>'s fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-Travellor, to St. <hi>Alban</hi>'s.</p>
            <p>He was mightily ſurpriz'd at the ſight of her; and could not but conclude now, that ſhe was in earneſt, and had a real Paſſion for him.</p>
            <p>He led her up to his da kſom Appart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, where he began to expreſs the ſenſe he had of the Houſe, and Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhe then did him in that Viſit. She told him he miſtook, for the kindneſs was to her ſelf only, and that ſhe was come with a full firm Reſolution to know what he refuſed to tell her, ſome Days paſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="158" facs="tcp:153254:85"/>
               <hi>But (Madam,</hi> interrupted he.) <hi>Firſt, I beſeech you let me know how you found me out here.</hi> Marwoud, <hi>with much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaty inform'd me</hi> (ſaid ſhe.) <hi>But had he known that I intended you a Viſit, and upon what account, I dare believe a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Guinneys wou'd not have tempted him to the Diſcovery. For, in ſhort (I'l be free with you, tho you are ſo unjuſtly ſtrange to me) he loves me; at leaſt I am confident he has a great Paſſion for my Money and Eſtate. The Devil's in him for</hi> Ariadnes! (interrupted <hi>Polydor.</hi>) She ſeem'd to take no notice of what he ſaid but went on. <hi>Yet let his Pretences</hi> (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinu'd ſhe) <hi>be never ſo generous or ſo ſelf-Intereſs'd I cou'd never love him, much leſs ſince I have had the misfortune to ſee you, who ſo obſtinately deny me the leaſt place in your kind thoughts. Madam,</hi> (replyed <hi>Polydor) I beg of you for Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy's ſake do not do me ſo great an Injuſtice, as to believe what you have ſaid. Heaven knows, if it were poſſible; I wou'd Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice my Heart and all to the Service of Sir</hi> Francis Heartwel<hi>'s Siſter. This is meer Evaſion</hi> (cry'd <hi>Dorothea,) I cannot ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:153254:85"/>
what ſhou'd hinder but your own Inclination, and unleſs you will let me know the Obſtacle, I ſhall die in that Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Since then, Madam</hi> (ſaid <hi>Polydor.) you preſs me ſo cloſely to it, I dare not deny you that ſatisfaction; but I muſt conjure you by whatſoever has the dearest Influence on you, that you will be ſecret: I promiſe it,</hi> (cry'd ſhe) <hi>as I hope for any Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in your Love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He kiſs'd her Hand upon it: And told her of his Marriage with <hi>Ariadne,</hi> the Circumſtances and all the Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes that were Conſequences of it.</p>
            <p>She all the time ſeem'd the moſt trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled Creature that ever was: Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſhe Sigh'd, then held her Handker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief to her Eyes, till ſhe had made 'em look as if they had been ſo red with Weeping; then ſhe would turn them Amorouſly on his, and there hold 'em for a conſiderable time; then at laſt, with another pittous Sigh fetch'd from the very bottom of her Lungs, ſhee'd fix 'em Languiſhingly on the Ground. And twenty other little Arts ſhe practic'd,
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:153254:86"/>
(which you know, pretty Ladies are very expert in,) to make him believe how much concern'd ſhe was at the loſs of him.</p>
            <p>I will not ſay poſitively, that ſhe did really Weep; but I am apt to think ſhe might: For, Women (they ſay) have an excellent Talent that way! Now for my part, I wonder at it! Since, I ſwear to you, I can't ſhed a Tear an I were to Hang for want of a Tear, unleſs I cut Onions (which is a thing I ſeldom do) or take fine <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Snuſh; and that brings the Rheum partly thro my Eyes, (which truly I like as well as Sneezing, every whit. It clears my Head and do's me as much kindneſs as I expect from it, but theſe means you'l ſay, are too vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to be miſtaken for the effects of any Paſſion. But after all, if I were to cry for my Life; I would go to hear a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy or two, that I know.</p>
            <p>The Doleful Tale being over at laſt; after ſome little ſilence on both ſides; <hi>Dorothea</hi> began to lament afreſh the loſs of the only Man whom, as ſhe preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, ſhe could Love; and the more to
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:153254:86"/>
aggravate his Miſery; She told him her deſign in coming then to him, was abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely to know his laſt Determination, whether he could Love her as a Wife or no? And to have paid his Debt within a Weeks time, if he had Marry'd her; nay, farther, her extravagant Paſſion carry'd her! She offer'd yet to make him her Husband, and to retire with him to any other part of the Chriſtian World. He could not forbear kiſſing her Hand again and again, for ſo prodigious a kind Propoſition: But he declin'd it as modeſtly as 'twas poſſible any Man ſhould. He let her ſee how deſtructive it would be to her Reputation, how fatal to her Quiet, after a few Months when the Exceſs of her Paſſion was allay'd. Nay, and added very honeſtly, that it was not improbable that he ſhould grow ſick of a Wife that had ſo far loſt all that was valuable in this World; and then they would both prove moſt miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But Madam</hi> (continued he) <hi>I am very Confident that this is but a tryal of my Humour, and if I had accepted your offer,
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:153254:87"/>
you would only have mock'd my eaſineſs in believing your Virtue ſo weak and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guarded. You may think</hi> (ſaid ſhe) <hi>as advantageouſly of me and my Virtue as you pleaſe; but aſſure your ſelf, I doubt my Love would Sacrifice all to you. But —In the name of good Fortune</hi> (purſu'd ſhe) <hi>what happineſs can you propoſe to your ſelf with your</hi> Ariadne! <hi>The grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt I could wiſh</hi> (replyed he) <hi>were ſhe yet but Virtuous. But</hi> (perhaps, ſaid <hi>Dorothea) in that you ſuppoſe Impoſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities. However Madam</hi> (anſwered <hi>Polydor) I'l hope the beſt. Well!</hi> (ſaid <hi>Dorothea) I ſee you are deaf to the news of a better Life, and ſo I leave you: But with all the diſcontent imaginable, on my part:</hi> Saying ſo, ſhe aroſe from her Seat.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Polydor</hi> who had forgotten it all this while, now at laſt bethought him, that (happily) ſhe might have talked her ſelf thirſty; beg'd of her to accept of one Glaſs of Wine, and left her in haſt without expecting her anſwer, to ſend for it. Mean while ſhe took a Paper
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:153254:87"/>
out of her Pocket, which ſhe convey'd under his Gloves:</p>
            <p>When he returned, ſhe told him, ſhe neither could nor would ſtay to drink with him, for whom ſhe had loſt her ſelf; and in a ſeeming kind of a Pet, flung out of the Room: He followed her, and taking her hand led her to the Gate, all the way begging her to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it as it was, his Misfortune, not his Fault. She ſaid no more, than 'twas in his Power yet to make his Fortune good or bad, and therefore ſhe conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it was his fault. He took his leave very ſubmiſſively of her at the inmoſt Gate, looking on her with a very Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tential Face, which (may be) he put on, meerly to pleaſe her.</p>
            <p>When ſhe was gone, he went to his Melancholy Retreat. Where he refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted on the ſtrange Perverſneſs of his Fortune; to cheat him thus with a falſe Counterfeit <hi>Ariadne</hi> of a true one; for it was paſt all doubt with him, that the Lady who juſt left him was Sir <hi>Francis Heartwel</hi>'s Siſter and the Real <hi>Ariadne:</hi> So many Circumſtances there were to
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:153254:88"/>
confirm him in that Opinion, there was the Livery and the Coach which was near enough to be known to him for Sir <hi>Francis</hi>'s, and what was greater than all that! He was certain that one of 'em was really Footman to the Knight.</p>
            <p>Theſe and ſuch like Thoughts kept him in his Chamber for about half an Hour: When, taking up his Gloves to walk down to give his Fellow-Sufferers a Viſit; he ſaw the Paper <hi>Dorothea</hi> had left there.</p>
            <p>'Twas Superſcribed, <hi>to</hi> Polydor <hi>the Credulous.</hi> By way of Imitation of his <hi>Bleſſings of Adverſity.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>THE Fool and Eaſy ſoon are loſt</l>
               <l>In Snares which careful Men avoid,</l>
               <l>Or, which their Arts have ſoon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy'd;</l>
               <l>Too ſubtile to be made the Coz'ners Boaſt!</l>
               <l>Tho Love, or Money be the Bait,</l>
               <l>Their Heart excludes the guilded, gay deceit;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="165" facs="tcp:153254:88"/>No room is for the Shadow found:</l>
               <l>But ſafe in their own Policies they reſt.</l>
               <l>They in a Proſp'rous World, or Adverſe Fate are Bleſt;</l>
               <l>When the kind Soul do's ſtrait admit,</l>
               <l>Each fawing Paraſite!</l>
               <l>Takes him into his Boſom from the ground</l>
               <l>Nay, ſuffers him to play his part,</l>
               <l>Even in the inmoſt of his Heart;</l>
               <l>And in the higheſt Throne Triumphing lets him ſit!</l>
               <l>A Faith like wax to every one he lends,</l>
               <l>Which a ſoft Word ſoon melts or a Smile bends,</l>
               <l>Takes the Impreſſion of a <hi>Judas</hi>-Kiſs,</l>
               <l>As deep, as the kind ſtamp of Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs!</l>
            </q>
            <p>I think there was a Mock to every Stanza; but on my Word I have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten 'em. <hi>Polydor</hi> was amaz'd at the Reading 'em, nor could he imagin how <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey came there. 'Twas a Womans Hand he concluded, but 'twas a Hand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oo he had never been acquainted with! <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he had traced him in his ſerious ſtuff ſo
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:153254:89"/>
exactly, that he could not but Laugh heartily at it!</p>
            <p>He put them up very carefully and went on with his Charitable Deſign of Viſiting ſome poor Gentlemen in the Houſe that had wanted him for ſome hours, he was very pleaſant with them till Bed time. When he went to ſleep till about Six the next Morning. I don't hear that he complained much of his misfortune that Night.</p>
            <p>In the Morning about Eleven a Clock, came <hi>Harry</hi> and <hi>Tom</hi> to ſee him: And brought him news that on the Morrow in the Afternoon, his <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> would be ready, and he might hope to ſee St. <hi>George</hi>'s Church before Night.</p>
            <p>He was well enough pleaſed with their diligence in his buſineſs, but he wanted his third Friend <hi>Will. O</hi> (cry'd <hi>Harry) hee'l be here time enough to rob us of the beſt part of our Dinner. We have beſpoke three Diſhes at</hi> Fowlers, <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt two a Clock, and the Wine I ſuppoſe will be here within a quarter of an hour.</hi> He had ſcarce ſpoken e'r it was brought. They got once more the freedom of the
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:153254:89"/>
Lodge for their Impriſoned Friend; where they Dined aſſoon as <hi>Will</hi> came; which was preciſely at two, as near as I can remember. They were mighty pleaſant all the time and ſo we will leave 'em; to hear what was done all this while at Sir <hi>Francis</hi>'s.</p>
            <p>There had been (it ſeems) a ſtrange Cataſtrophe, for <hi>Dorothea</hi> and <hi>Miranda</hi> had now at laſt prevail'd on <hi>Ariadne</hi> to leave off Tormenting her <hi>Polydor</hi> and reſt ſatisfyed with his good qualities af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo many cruel Experiments ſhe had made on him. What moſt invited her to be at laſt Civill to him, was the decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of his Love for her which he made to <hi>Dorothea,</hi> ſuppoſing, ſhe might not have quite loſt her Virtue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Well!</hi> (ſaid <hi>Ariadne) I conſent to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceive my Enchanted Squire, on Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion you'l ſuffer me to diſcover your Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations; your's</hi> Miranda <hi>firſt to my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and yours</hi> Dorothea <hi>to</hi> Marwoud: <hi>Think not</hi> (purſued ſhe not permitting them to reply) <hi>that I ask this of ye as a favour too, no I have already reſolv'd on it; and as Good Fortune will have it, ſee
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:153254:90"/>
here they both come.—Come Brother</hi> (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſhe) <hi>pray ſit and Oblige Mr.</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woud <hi>to ſit with us: We muſt Conſult, here is much buſineſs to be done, and that very ſuddainly. Nay; if I can ſerve you Madam;</hi> (replyed <hi>Marwoud) you need but inſtruct me, and conclude affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matively of my abſolute Obedience. You promiſe largely and nobly</hi> (replyed <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adne) but I fear you will repent of your Obligation: Tho in my Opinion you have rather cauſe to be ſatisfyed with it. And, not to hold you any longer in ſuſpence, know 'twas with my conſent and the beſt of my Affections and Endeavours that I Marry'd</hi> Polydor; <hi>and you have only been my Inſtrument in trying his humour, which otherwiſe I could not have been ſo well acquainted with. Now, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> (continued ſhe) <hi>the Requeſt or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand (which you pleaſe to call it) that I have to you; is to lay aſide all Animoſities to him and Pretenſions to his Wife: Not that I mean to rob you of one Miſtreſs and leave you abſolutely deſtitute of an Object of Love; no; I ſhall rather make you too ample ſatisfaction for ſo inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:153254:90"/>
a loſs, when I dare promiſe you and offer you now the Heart of my Dear</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rothea, <hi>I expect no denyal after the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe you have given me: 'tis partly an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment you ought to make me, for the opportunities I have ſhewn you of gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying your Revenge on your Friend and my Husband. In ſhort, I deſign you ſhall be happy with her the ſame day that I am ſo with</hi> Polydor. <hi>Madam</hi> (ſaid <hi>Marwoud) ſince you do really Love</hi> Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, <hi>and that there is now no longer any hope for me from your Circumſtances, I can't propoſe greater felicity to my ſelf than</hi> Dorothea's <hi>Love, if I cou'd be aſſured on't. I will engage for it</hi> (anſwered <hi>Ariadne) Pray make your Addreſſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They then fell into Cabals, <hi>Ariadne</hi> diſcourſing her Brother and <hi>Miranda.</hi> There ſhe did <hi>Miranda</hi> the violence to diſcover the Paſſion ſhe ſo long had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain'd for Sir <hi>Francis,</hi> who was moſt pleaſantly ſurpriſed with the Relation, and blam'd his Siſter that ſhe had not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed it before, that he might ha' Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry'd aſſoon as ſhe. Something ſhe ſaid to excuſe it; but that is not very Mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial here.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="170" facs="tcp:153254:91"/>
               <hi>Marwoud</hi> was very well pleaſed with the Perſon and Humour of his new Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, but ſtill he had a Reluctance or uneaſineſs in his thoughts for the loſs of <hi>Ariadne</hi>'s Fortunes: <hi>Dorothea</hi> was very well contented with his Humour, Perſon and Fortunes; for to ſay truth, ſhe had lov'd him long, and could have accepted him with half his Eſtate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ariadne</hi> having brought things to ſo good a Period at home, propos'd the day following, to undeceive the poor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponding <hi>Polydor.</hi> In order to which, Sir <hi>Francis</hi> and <hi>Miranda, Marwo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d</hi> and <hi>Dorothea</hi> accompany'd her to him. <hi>Ariadne</hi> deſir'd to ſpeak with him, and one of the Servants went to acquaint him that the Lady was at the Gate that came to viſit Him with a Gentlewoman, three or four days paſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Polydor</hi> bid the Fellow ſay <hi>he was buſy,</hi> as indeed he was, for there were his three Friends who had brought his <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> to remove him. The Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſenger return'd for all that, and told him th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>dy was to Impo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> that to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny'd,
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:153254:91"/>
that ſhe muſt ſpeak with him. Tell her ſhe may <hi>(ſaid Polydor)</hi> If ſhe will take the pains to meet me three or four hours hence at the <hi>Golden Lyon</hi> in <hi>Southwark.</hi> He did ſo, and return'd once more to let <hi>Polydor</hi> know that Sir <hi>Francis Heartwell</hi> would ſee him if he pleaſed. Sir <hi>Francis Heartwell!</hi> (cry'd <hi>Polydor</hi> in a great ſurpriſe!) <hi>Thou miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takeſt ſure. No Sir</hi> (reply'd the Servant) <hi>ſo he call'd himſelf, I am certain. D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> him, let him come in</hi> (ſaid Harry) <hi>If he do</hi>'s <hi>affront thee, I ſhall find a time to cut his throat. I cannot blame thy zeal for thy friend</hi> (replyed <hi>Polydor) tho it be miſtaken. He is a man of too much honour to offer any Rudeneſs.</hi> Saying ſo, he went as far as he might to wait on Sir <hi>Francis,</hi> who was juſt coming into the Houſe with his Siſter, <hi>Marwoud</hi> leading <hi>Miranda</hi> and <hi>Dorothea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After having ſaluted each other, Sir <hi>Francis</hi> deſir'd <hi>Polydor</hi> to leave his friends to entertain one other for a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of an hour, that he might diſcourſe him a little privately. <hi>Polydor</hi> ſpoke to 'em of it, and went into another
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:153254:92"/>
Room with the two Gentlemen and the Ladys. <hi>Sir,</hi> (ſaid the Knight, lifting up his Siſter's hood, which till then cover'd her face) <hi>Do you not know this Lady? Too well Sir</hi> (Reply'd <hi>Polydor) you had not found me here, Sir, otherwiſe. Have you any pretentions to her?</hi> (ſaid Sir <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis.) Pretentions, Sir</hi> (anſwer'd <hi>Polydor) no, no; and I wou'd ſhe never had had any for me! What's the meaning of this?</hi> (ſaid the Knight;) <hi>To my knowledge ſhe loves you. Do you know who ſhe is? Yes, and what ſhe is too,</hi> (reply'd <hi>Polydor;) ſhe call's her ſelf</hi> Ariadne; <hi>but the pretty Impoſture will not paſs for ſuch in this Lady's Company.</hi> At theſe words, he took <hi>Dorothea</hi>'s hand. <hi>'Tis well</hi> (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued he) <hi>they are both come together. I hope my</hi> Ariadne <hi>will not any longer pretend to the blood of the</hi> Heartwells <hi>before you, Sir. Your</hi> Ariadne! (ſaid Sir <hi>Francis) why, are you Marry'd to either of 'em; Yes, yes, Sir</hi> Francis (cry'd he in a great Paſſion) <hi>To my eternal ſhame I am marri'd to this falſe Beautifull crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; yes I am ſped with her. Well Sir,</hi> (anſwer'd <hi>Ariadnes</hi> Brother) <hi>And
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:153254:92"/>
Heaven give you joy with my Siſter! Ah Sir</hi> (ſays <hi>Polydor) Do not triumph in the misfortunes of an unhappy Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man! I know you do but Impoſe now; for that Lady's your Siſter,</hi> (ſaid he bowing to <hi>Dorothea.) If you pleaſe Sir, (anſwer'd</hi> Marwoud) <hi>That Lady ſhall be my Wife before Noon yet, as late as 'tis. It ſhall onely trouble me</hi> (replyed <hi>Polidor) for the Lady</hi>'s <hi>ſake. Come, come,</hi> Polydor, (ſaid his kind b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>other in Law) <hi>pen your Eyes, view her well! Is not your</hi> Ariadne <hi>more like me than my Couſin</hi> Dorothea? <hi>for ſo is that Lady call'd who has hitherto only perſonated my Siſter, the more to perplex you. Ah</hi> Polydor cry'd <hi>Ariadne) I bring thee now thy True and Faithfull</hi> Ariadne. <hi>Let me embrace you together (ſaid</hi> Sir <hi>Francis.) And now</hi> Polydor (cryd <hi>Marwoud</hi> taking him by the hand) <hi>Let here all Picques and Feuds ceaſe. I wiſh thee, and will not envy thee, all thoſe joys thou art like to poſſeſs in that Lady; To whoſe Embraces and careſſes I will at preſent leave you, to withdraw the Action that is againſt you; which I proteſt I do, with much more content than
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:153254:93"/>
I lay'd it on. Ha!</hi> (cryed <hi>Polydor) This is too much happineſs for me in one day! To find my dear</hi> Ariadne <hi>true, to be reconcil'd to my friend whom I thought paſt it, and to be ſo nearly ally'd to one whom I have always been ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious of ſerving.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Marwoud</hi> went out and diſcharg'd him of the Action and fees of the Houſe, while the other two Ladys complemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him; and began to confeſs how they had all contributed to his ſeeming misfortunes. <hi>Heaven (cry'd</hi> Polydor) <hi>that I ſhould not know that face again and that ſhape out of Breeches. But I am now awake. Yet</hi> (continued he) <hi>I muſt beg you would permit me to diſtruſt your kindneſs to me before my friends, in t' other Room: Be it as your humour Commands</hi> (anſwer'd <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adne) But don't let the counterfit laſt long.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Marwou'd</hi> now return'd and brought news of <hi>Polydors</hi> Libertie: who ſtrait led 'um to his other Friend. After Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements had paſſ'd, he call'd his three Friends aſide, and told 'um how things had ſucceeded, but withall added, that he durſt not yet truſt their Kindneſs, where
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:153254:93"/>
fore he intreated they wou'd ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ompany him to Sir <hi>Francis</hi>'s, where he was go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and that he wou'd plant 'em ſo near, that upon the leaſt call they might come to his aſſiſtance if occaſion were. They all promiſed to hazard their Lives and Fortunes in his Service.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Polydor</hi> then taking ſome Money out of his Pocket to beſtow on the poor wretches that wanted it, at the ſame time pull'd out the mock to his Pinda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rique; and ſhew'd it to <hi>Dorothea,</hi> asking <hi>if ſhe knew the hand.</hi> She anſwer'd, yes, <hi>'twas her Conſin</hi> Ariadnes; who ſmiling, confeſs'd that ſhe had ſtolen his melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly ſtuff with deſign to abuſe it. He was not a little pleas'd with this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion.</p>
            <p>As ſoon as every one had Diſtributed their Charities, they left the diſmal place, and <hi>Polydor</hi> took Coach with Sir <hi>Francis, Ariadne, Miranda, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wou'd</hi> and <hi>Dorothea:</hi> But <hi>Harry, Will</hi> and <hi>Tom</hi> were forc'd to walk into <hi>Cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide,</hi> where they likewiſe took a Hackny Coach, following Sir <hi>Francis</hi>'s Coach, as cloſe as they could. They came in
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:153254:94"/>
time to their Journey's end: Where <hi>Polidor</hi> diſpos'd of his three merry Boys in a very convenient Room, leaving 'em Wine enough to ſupply 'em till he had diſpatch'd his affairs in the next Room. Where as ſoon as he came, he was amaz'd to ſee the Tables already ſpread, and all things in as much order as if it had been deſign'd a week before! But this was not all the occaſion of his ſurprize, for when his Brother in Law, and his dear <hi>Ariadne,</hi> led him into an Inner Room, he was there preſented with all the Writings of her Eſtate, and a glorious ſight of Rich Jewells, and of Gold and Silver, ſome in Bags and ſome looſly ſcatter'd about the Cheſt. This ſight was not altogether ungrateful to <hi>Polydor,</hi> tho he did not abſolutely do at on Riches.</p>
            <p>Immediately after the ſhew was over, Sir <hi>Francis</hi> was for calling for the Perſon whom he had provided to ſpeak ſome fatal words, (as ſtrong as any Witches Charm, I'm ſure) to him and <hi>Marwou'd,</hi> and the other two Ladys. But <hi>Polydor</hi> beg'd his three
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:153254:94"/>
Friends might firſt be admitted; to which they agreed: and he gave the ſign immediately for them to come in. Who no ſooner heard it, but with all the Violence and Reſolution imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, they ruſh'd in with their Swords drawn. <hi>Ha!</hi> (cry'd <hi>Polydor) whence is this Rudeneſs! what do you mean Gentlemen! How now</hi> Polydor (ſaid <hi>Harry) Have you forgot we came to your Reſcue? Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to Divorce me from the greateſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs imaginable</hi> (reply'd he drawing his Sword, which Sir <hi>Francis</hi> and <hi>Marwou'd</hi> did likewiſe) <hi>This is ſtrange</hi> (ſaid <hi>Will.) It is indeed</hi> (anſwer'd <hi>Polydor) very ſtrange; that a man ſhould betray himſelf into twelve hundred a year beſides thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands in Money and Jewels, and throw himſelf away on ſo Beautifull a Creature as</hi> Ariadne. <hi>You</hi> (Harry) <hi>I confeſs might have expected it? but for ſuch a perſon as mine. Death we are fool'd then</hi> (cry d <hi>Tom) well we ſhall find a time</hi> (continu'd he offering to go.) <hi>Hold Gentlemen, pray be'nt angry</hi> (ſaid <hi>Polydor) you muſt not go yet, till you have din'd with us, and been Witneſſes to a little
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:153254:95"/>
Buſineſs that theſe two Gentlemen and Ladies have to diſpatch, Come, Put up! Put up! We are all friends. Ay, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen</hi> (ſaid Sir <hi>Francis) we muſt intreat your Company to day. Nay</hi> (added <hi>Marwou'd) ye muſt be our Gueſs.</hi> Upon this they all put up; and were as good as ſo many Certificates to <hi>Miranda</hi> and <hi>Dorothea;</hi> that Ceremony ended, they eat and drank plentifully, had the Fid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles, Danc'd, and were wondrous Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, ſo wee'l leave 'em till night, when I ſuppoſe the three Hero's went to Bed with their Ladys; where wee'l leave 'em to be more Happy, than I dare tell you they were.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:153254:95"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153254:96"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153254:96" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
